This meeting of April 29th,
2026 is called to order, and
I will ask Dr. Entwistle to take the
call.
DeAngelis.
Here.
Feller.
Holman.
Here.
Richardson.
Rish.
Here.
Smith.
Cabissa.
Davison.
So just as an opening statement,
as this is a public meeting, unless the Board of Education specifically
votes to enter into executive session, the public has the
right to hear everything and to look at all exhibits.
Please let us know if you experience any difficulties with accessibility.
Members of the district staff are located in the lecture hall to
provide assistance. The school board works from a prepared
agenda, which is posted in advance on the district
website, and printed copies of this evening's agenda
are available near the entrance of the lecture hall.
Fellow board members to please remember that Robert's Rules of
Order states that members may speak no more than twice on the same item
at any one meeting, except by permission of the chair.
Questions, brief suggestions, or points of clarification are
not counted as speaking in debate.
The board asks that the public audience refrain from clapping, booing,
side comments, or other behaviors that could interrupt the flow of speakers.
Every person is entitled to speak their opinion and to feel safe in the process.
Thank you.
The first is final budget
decisions.
That's you.
I'm sorry. Final budget decisions.
That's the report of the chair.
Well, in the report of the chair, I'm not doing final budget
decisions, because we're not taking those motions.
So I can go to the superintendent search update if you want. Okay.
Superintendent search update, and I will turn to
Vice Chair Smith.
The South Portland School Board would like to announce it has two finalists for the
position of superintendent of schools.
There will be a community meet and greet of the two candidates from 6:00 to
7:00 PM on Wednesday, May 6th, at South Portland Middle
School. Each candidate will have a half-hour slot, so if you'd like to meet both
candidates, please plan to spend the full hour there.
Posters will be on the middle school doors, and further details will be posted on
the school website. Please reserve this date and time.
Thank you.
So we are up to
the report of the superintendent.
There's been a tremendous amount of input
provided by families, staff, community members,
by way of listening sessions, surveys, and
emails, with more than 1,000 individuals sharing their
thoughts.
This does not include input received by individuals
in public comment in sessions like this.
And
those meetings have been held through the fall, the winter,
and the spring.
Dr. Johanna Prince
did
an extraordinary job, most recently with listening
sessions, and we do have a report
of
what we've learned, basically. And Myra, I understand you're going to
do that. And
Andy, this is when we switch to the other
presentation mode.
Good evening. I am Myra Karen, principal at Kahler,
and I'm going to share a little bit about
the findings from the community
engagement sessions, along with my colleagues
from the two other schools. So just wanted to
start by saying
that there were several different ways in which we
listened to a variety of people. The
question was the same in all of the forums in which we
did this, and so that was: what are your questions, concerns, and
opportunities as we plan this change, and what do you want us to hold
onto along the way? So that question was asked in every
situation. And we listened in five different ways, which
I will go into a little bit more in a minute.
And many of those were in-person
sessions,
and also online
for every elementary school. And we conducted a survey,
the union conducted a survey, and then, of course, letters and
emails. And we have organized this
by staff, families, and community, and came up with
a couple of different themes to share with you in addition
to the next steps.
So,
these are some of the numbers to share with you.
It was 14 listening sessions that were conducted in
all. You can see seven staff, six family, and
one special education
session.And this includes
about 328
participants
in person, but also that does include
online.
And the survey that was sent out was through
ThoughtExchange and was open to anyone to take, that
was
476 people, which is about
303 completed it, so 64%.
As we heard at the last meeting, the teachers' union
conducted a survey
and shared some of those results. Those results are linked here as well,
and that was 187 participants.
And
emails to both the district
administration and you as the board members
included 50 plus
pieces of communication.
You're not expected to be looking at all of these slides as I
flip through them. They are available online.
Principal Hopkins is going to
share with you some of the
themes that emerged
from the surveys.
I know that's much more exciting.
Oops.
There you go. Thanks.
Hi. Allison Hopkins, principal at Dyer Elementary School.
So as Mair shared, really the question that was asked were
questions and concerns,
and even ideas around the
process towards reconfiguration and where we found that
all of these results converged, the voices converged, were
really families, all stakeholders wanting to know why, and
even from you all, we've heard data.
Like, what's the data behind these decisions?
Really with the closure of Keller, honoring that
school family through the closure.
Protecting our students, our most vulnerable population, students with
IEPs, our youngest learners. Lots of families, as we've
heard,
their love for the community school and being able to walk to
school,
and sort of being a school where they live.
Communication was also pretty big across the board, the district, and
the community.
Staff wanting to have a realistic runway to do this well.
I think we all want that. And those
relationships that students have with familiar adults within their building.
So, no matter if someone supported or
disagreed with reconfiguration, these were themes that came out of both
sides.
And then really the difference,
the two big sort of areas, the tension was pretty
real. You have one side who is
really set on equity is the reason to proceed in
a timely manner. And these voices
really came from Keller and Skillen staff, special
educators, and some family members at every school,
noting that the current configuration itself is a
problem, and acting now is the right response.
And then the other side,
really the neighborhood is the reason to slow down.
And many of these voices came from Brown, Small, and Dyer families,
with some staff at
each school saying that this model has real value.
Like the connections between the kindergarten and fourth graders, and
that the timeline is part of
the reason to not do this at this time.
And asking all of these students to move may not
deliver the equity it names. So,
those were where the voices differed.
And I will now let Principal Connolly wrap up.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Bethany Connolly. I'm the principal at Skillen.
So a few through lines that came
out
in all of the listening sessions were about the quality of the
process.
And some questions that people had about the process
that we've undertaken, I think as a board and as a district,
around being clear with our rationale,
showing the data, trade-offs, decision-making
criteria.
I think families and staff both
wanted more of an active part in the creation of the
plan and not reactive-
Principal Connolly, I'm going to stop you for one second just to give a round of
applause to that custodian who just helped us with that clock.
Okay, so-
Thank you.
That would've made us crazy. Thank you. Thank you very much.
Okay. I'm sorry. Go ahead.
Nothing worse than looking at a clock and thinking, "Oh, I still have all this
time."
Right. Exactly. Thank you.
The
next thing is consistent messaging.
I think
that the process this year, feedback was
there is inconsistency in board messaging, district
messaging,
aligning what we're communicating to
our community, our staff, and our families.
Realistic prep and planning time
is something that came upAcross staff and families,
extending the planning window was, I think, the most concrete
response we got.
Asking just for
more time to be very thoughtful
about the process and give the opportunities for
building some of that clarity and looping in all
stakeholders to the process. And which leads us to the visible
feedback loop,
which is in relation to the creation of a steering
committee that includes all stakeholders, staff,
families, community members, with a clear
timeline,
expectations for when
that steering committee would report out on the work and the decisions being made,
and provide regular updates to the board and the community.
And so based on
all of the feedback from all of the different
sessions and surveys,
developed
these priorities and next steps. So
for students, we want to make sure that they have
a sense of stability and belonging and familiar faces,
try to minimize disruption, move cohorts of students
together.
We always want to pay attention to the mental health of our students,
and make sure we have clear routines and still are able to
infuse joy in our schools, which I can tell you from walking around
today, it's still happening every day in
classrooms. We have the best teachers. We have amazing kids.
They're doing it.
And then real transition supports.
And I think those transition supports before the first day are for
students, but also it's not in the staff column or the
family column, but I think
everybody needs some support with the transition.
For staff,
I think this is right now probably one of the most challenging things
for our staff who are doing all the great work with our kids every day,
is certainty about placement, where they're going to be, what
they're going to be teaching, who they're going to be doing that with.
Needing paid time to pack and move and build new
teams. That's not something that we would ask our teachers to do
on their own time.
Team continuity where possible was a priority, and then
having a voice in staffing and program decisions.
And then for families, again, back to that clear
communication, being honest and transparent about our
timelines.
Really taking into consideration all those logistical things that parents need
to have in place in order to do the
Herculean task of getting children out the door every day and where they need to
be.
And then community building across our schools,
so that, I think we all
have recognized that this is, in some ways, a good problem
to have. People love their schools.
They love their school communities because we have amazing schools.
So building community across our schools,
I think would help our whole community see the
positives that exist within each unique school community.
And then real partnerships and not just
sharing of information, but having that iterative
feedback loop and participation.
So a steering committee is being formed with staff,
families, community members
to take these findings and turn them into a plan.
I think that's it.
Mm-hmm.
Thank you.
All right.
We're not
going
to
talk amongst
you
all?
All right. Good evening, everyone.
I'm Abigail Ketchen, finance director,
and I'm here to talk about
our final budget.
Next slide, please.
Okay. So I want to talk a little bit about
where I think we're going financially and where I think it's possible
to be.
I think we have to be on a path to
financial well-being.
I want to see us out of this cycle of
strife, of overspending, then we have to figure that out.
And
I would pose that success looks like
a district focused on education.
When the finance function is working smoothly,
we are not at the forefront. We're in the background running smoothly.
And for me,
my financial vision is definitely that
education is the star of all of our conversations,
and that financial operations, including emergencies,
are addressed smoothly and in the background.
I
aim to see next year's employment just be something that's
assumed.
And audit issues,
when everything's running smoothly, really should be rare and then addressed
quickly.
So I want to say that is what I think success looks like for us
financially as a district.
And I-
I don't say 100%
very often, but I do believe that this is possible.
I don't think it's possible instantly.
I think we're a couple of years away from feeling this,
but I do think that this is a place we could be one
day. And it's what I'm striving for, for
sure.
I think there's a few points for how we do that.
Number one, we accept help where help is there, such as
from our city partners. And I'll talk about that in the next
slide. We should accept help to help stabilize our
financial foundation, so that we can be on our
own feet moving forward.
As we make decisions, we should be investing solely in what is most
essential to our core mission. And that's a question we should be
asking ourselves every day, but certainly as the big
decisions come along.
We must reduce expenses wherever we cannot reasonably sustain this year
after year. So the question we should be asking is, "Okay, can we afford
this the year after, and the year after, and the year after with a
reasonable escalation?"
Guardrails are incredibly important.
We do strongly recommend some sort of minimum savings policy.
I think that will really help us. It will be a guardrail that we can rely
on
when the pressure happens
to not do that. A policy really does provide
that sentiment we can rely on.
Certainly, a focus on the quality of our decisions around hiring,
what we do for retention, our operations, our day-to-day,
and our planning.
Just the quality of our planning is a key area for us to
continue to improve and grow. And then more internally,
our own focus on continuous operational efficiencies.
Looking for efficiencies, it's of course a great idea every
budget season,
but it's an even better idea all the time.
So that's something that is certainly what I will be emphasizing in
my finance meetings with directors and administrators, is how we can
continuously improve and make things work smoothly for everybody, while
being financially responsible.
Next slide.
Okay.
So last night, we met with city council, and they
gave us some updated guidance.
I think something that we have really to celebrate
is that we
received their general sentiment to
support up to $2 million of our projected deficit for this
year.
So as you all know, for those of you who have been watching along, we are
projecting a deficit for this fiscal year.
We've already expended all of our fund balance, and what that means is that
the deficit this year,
by default,
is taken from the city's fund balance.
And what we had last night was just a confirmation of
their
agreement, their understanding that they're willing to
forgive up to $2 million, which means that we would not necessarily--
It would mean that we don't need to be on a payment plan and pay it back,
which would be something that would really hold us back,
both in FY28 and until we had paid that off.
So this is an incredibly
generous
action,
and I think that we owe it to the city, we owe it to
all taxpayers, and we owe it to ourselves to take full
advantage of this opportunity.
We have to make the most of it and make really solid decisions moving
forward, have strong budgeting, and make good decisions.
And I fully believe that we can do that.
We also received some general guidance to stay at the 6%
tax increase. I heard some up to 7% at the
meeting. I heard some stay at 6% at the meeting.
So there's that for you all to consider.
And then what we're looking ahead to is the May 5th, the city council
vote, and then eventually a public vote on June 9th.
Do you have a question?
Yes. Are there questions?
I have one, but I'm going to wait and see if anybody has any others.
Yeah, please.
I just had one question about the
emphasis on efficiencies with the hires.
Could you speak into the mic?
Yeah. I don't know why.
Is that better?
Okay.
We
talked about this at the last meeting, and we've talked about this kind of offline
a bit, but
focusing on the process for MainCare reimbursement and-
Mm-hmm
... kind of highlighting,
analyzing that current process and if there's any kind of additional training or
support-
Mm-hmm
...
or enhancements that we can make to that process to make it easier on folks to
submit those reimbursements.
Mm-hmm. Yeah. So it's not just the expense side, it's also the revenue side-
Right
... of our efficiencies and how we operate.
Yes. MainCare reimbursements,
it's definitely a focus. I think we may have more work to do on ensuring that we
are getting all that we can be reimbursed for.
But I know it is a focus,
and especially for our Director of Instructional Support, Kate Cox.
Is it possible to have an update on that in a couple of months, like what we
found out and what we learned from-
Mm-hmm.
Mm-hmm
... if we identified room for improvement and...
Mm-hmm. Yep.
Okay. Thank you.
Abigail, I just had one question. One of the questions that came through
today in an email was
about the
city's
expectations about this money and
their expectations about
if we were to be in this bind again, what their expectations would be
and what ours would be. So if you might speak to that, it would be helpful.
Mm-hmm.
My expectation is to not be in this bind at all.
So my expectation is that is a moot point.
I would think that the city would expect not to be
so forgiving next year.
Okay.
I think this is an incredible year, it's an incredible opportunity, and
the ball's in our court to take advantage of this and be on a better
path.
Thank you.
Member Fowler.
Abigail, any developments on generating revenue from Keller?
No. Nothing new. Thank you.
Do you see a path forward there?
I don't know. I know the idea was maybe we could rent it out.
For me, that's an idea.
So I would want to see if that's possible.
Do you know what process by which we would go ahead and explore those
opportunities? Would that be your responsibility, would it be someone else's
responsibility?
I don't know. It's not finance, but I don't know exactly.
I'll turn that question over to the superintendent.
Yeah.
I was going to say, it would probably be a team that would be working on something
like that.
Yeah. And I
do want to double-click on that because that revenue could
potentially support student-facing positions or could pad the fund balance.
So I don't want to lose sight of that opportunity.
It was terrible what we had to do. But if we could generate
some revenue, that would be important.
Thanks. I'm all set.
Thank you. Any other questions?
Mm-hmm. I can go to the next slide.
Go ahead.
Okay.
Next slide, please.
So we've had one update. We received a one-time main
supplemental funding allotment of 153,000.
So at this point, that has been added into the budget.
That has had an effect on personnel.
We were able to add another teacher back on a one-time basis,
because this funding is one time.
And of course, as the funding picture changes, we would be open to
exploring that and seeing what's possible.
Again,
funding needs to be something consistent year to year, that we have a reasonable
expectation of assuming that will happen year to year for a
personnel decision to be
more than one year. So we are looking to that.
But that has been updated at this point. Next slide.
Okay.
So these are our expenses cost centers.
There's not a lot that has changed.
We've done a little bit of updating just with some actual names
as resignations, et cetera, have come in.
Some people have shuffled around a little bit, so we've made adjustments for
that. And then we've moved around some contingencies
a little bit, which I'll explain in the next slide.
You can go ahead. Mm-hmm. Okay.
So when we think about contingencies,
we've been talking about that $179,000 figure that we added.
But we do want to be transparent about other areas where
there could be wiggle room, but we just don't know yet.
So we just wanted to point out, there's $25,000 in moving
stipends. We'll see how much we actually use.
Will it be all of that? Will it be a little more, a little less?
We have that $250,000 plug for IEP meetings
and time beyond 15 hours.
And then there's the rest, contingencies within the Board of Education's cost
center, the $75,000 in moving
expenses, and then a little bit extra for other unexpected
costs.
So when we think about contingencies, it's a little bit beyond
that 179,000, but not totally because the other things
are for something. We just don't know exactly how much it's going to
be. But that will be something that we're going to keep a close eye on
throughout the year.
I'll be happy to report on that on a monthly basis.
But that's where there's potentially some
wiggle room. And it will take time to find out really
how much we're talking about. And certainly, by
the mid FY27, we'll have a much better idea about the
IEP meeting real costs, and then that will better
inform the FY28 budget.
Thank you.
Then the next slide.
So at this point, I will turn it over to Dr.
Prince to talk about our final personnel changes.
Chair. Madam Chair.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Is it-
I'm sorry, Abigail, just to be sure there weren't any questions.
Yeah. Is it-
Because I think there's one.
Yeah. Is it possible to ask you a question-
Yes
... about the previous slide before-
... we sit down?
Yes, go ahead.
Go back one slide, please.
Mm-hmm.
A couple of questions. Do we have any idea what
we have
spent on
meetings beyond 15 hours at this point for this year?
No, we are still working that out. We are still working that out.
So is that
potentially
going
to hit FY26?
Yes.
And we-
Yes
... and we don't know what that is-
That's correct
... at all.
I don't know at all as of today. We do see some
time sheets rolling in and there's back-and-forth emails and
discussions about this, but I don't have a solid figure right
now.
Do we-
If I did, I would want to inform this.
Exactly.
Yeah.
That's why I was trying to figure out how we ended up with this 250,000.
We originally ended up with 250,000 from
some working out the number of meetings, number of
people in meetings. I worked with Cat Cox on an estimation,
but we did detail out pretty specifically like, okay,
there's this many meetings, this many people, then we minused out 15 hours from
each of those people, and we landed
around 245, and then there's another calculation done that landed
around 235. I put in 250
as a plug for now. Mm-hmm.
Thank you. So that means that
the due diligence you worked through with Cat-
Mm-hmm
... helped to understand potentially how many meetings have
occurred?
Oh, yes.
Over 50.
Yes. Yeah. And she looked-
I was thinking just how you-
... through her files and... No. We started with a pretty good number
of meetings, and then we extrapolated from there based on how many people are in
the meetings, how long they last-
Okay
... all of that. It came from somewhere,
but it is an estimate.
Okay.
Yeah, and if I can clarify, I think, Member Richardson, this is for
FY27.
I know it.
Going forward. Okay.
Yeah.
Okay.
But we-
I'm trying to get clear with what's going on too.
But there is a figure we don't know for-
Got you
... FY26.
Exactly. Right.
Have you included an
estimate?
I know you got pretty comfortable with
up to $2 million-
Mm-hmm
...
for our deficit. Are you
feeling comfortable
that this unknown figure
is in there,
is kind of baked in there?
I feel pretty comfortable.
Yeah.
Okay.
I
don't do blustering confidence. You know what I mean?
No.
I'm not going to just-
It's not a fair question. I understand that.
I feel pretty comfortable. Mm-hmm.
But I want to be honest where-
Yeah
... there's some unknowns.
And this is because we have a new system we're putting into place.
Yes.
So this isn't always going to be
an issue every year.
No.
Yeah. Okay.
Yeah, no. Halfway through FY27, I'm going to have a very clear
idea
for sure. Yeah.
Okay.
Member Holman.
Just for the layperson, the notes are kind of interesting.
I think contingency for board of education, what does that mean
specifically? It makes it sound like it's a board expense.
Well, it's placed in the cost center six system administration.
That cost center includes the board of education's office
and other offices as well.
It's placed there because it's close to the legal expenses-
Okay
... area.
Okay. That's all right.
Yeah.
All right. Okay.
Mm-hmm.
And then it says 75K moving in contingency, but there's
97,000, so it's-
Mm-hmm
... 75K moving plus other contingency.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, good. Thank you.
Yeah.
So that 179-
Member Fowler.
Oh, sorry.
That 179,000 number that you presented before
as being what was likely going into reserve fund, is that from
the bottom two numbers, 83 and 97?
Yeah. And yeah. Mm-hmm.
Okay, great. Also, while I have the mic, I just want to thank you
publicly, Abigail. You're not only very good at math, but you're
also a storyteller, and as a new board member, you've really helped me come
up to speed with where things are. So just thank you so much.
Aw, thank you. Thank you very much.
Abigail, I just had a last question, and it was following up on what Member
Richardson said.
So
when you come out with this number from
FY26, whatever that is, is that how we
get money
that goes from contingency into fund balances?
If we come under whatever it is that's budgeted, your alter
ego is nodding behind you, so
but-
Yeah, so in
this new budget, FY27, if we land with a surplus, that surplus
will be swept into fund balance.
Okay.
That's how money gets in there.
Got you.
Mm-hmm.
Okay, thank you. Just trying to get that clear. Thank you.
Any other questions?
Okay, keep going.
Okay.
Do you want me to change that?
We're just going to change over computer really quickly.
While we are doing that, I'm Johanna Prince, Assistant Superintendent.
Board members, you should have a printout of the next document that I'm
going to talk about. Those of you that are listening at home or in the
audience, these slides are linked to the FY27 webpage,
and this document that we're going to look at in a minute is linked on slide
10.
So what we'd like to talk about with the budget is just a really
clear understanding of what positions were
eliminated and what positions remain within the unit,
because we've been at this process now for almost two months, and
things have gone in and out.
So wanted to make sure that the board and the public are clear
as to where we've landed. So again, off of slide 10,
there is linked a two-page spreadsheet, and
I'll walk the board and the public through them.
One of these should present a
summary. Important to note that every single position in our
district is not represented on this list.
We have some non-bargaining folks who are neither lunch aides nor
directors. Because that segment of our staff was not
impacted, it's not reflected
here.So, what you're
looking at in column B is the type of
position grouped within the bargaining unit, or non-bargaining is
what NB stands for. In column C, you're
looking at how many positions
existed in the current school year.
That is not necessarily a full-time equivalent, because some people are part-time,
but this is individual, unique positions that
exist across those roles. In column
D, what you're looking at is the final impact
to that line item.
And then in column E, you're looking at, for the
next fiscal year, how many
positions remain in that
category. So it goes through non-bargaining, our
service,
our SPESA, which is clerks, ed techs, and office
managers, our SPAA, which is administrators,
and then the teachers.
Down below, because it's been a focus of the board's attention,
we did draw out some specific
SPTA or teacher data so that folks
could see how that had progressed through our
conversations.
So talking specifically first about case managers in
the elementary, middle, and high school, and then the instructional strategist
roles. And then down below are the group that
we refer to as our service providers, and being clear both
about how many of those positions exist now, what the change
was, and what we have for next year.
On the next tab,
and this should be on a different page for the board
members, what we wanted to do is just break that out
into even greater clarity around
exactly where those positions were and what titles and roles.
This is not something that we have done in the past with as much
clarity, and it's an improvement that I'm pleased that we're
bringing forward just so that we can all leave this process
with a real clear list
of impacts.
So again, just the detail here of exactly
what those positions are that are embedded in an
action item this evening where the board does need to take
action to reduce these positions
contractually.
I'd love to present the next slide and then pause for
questions about positions. I think that
one of the things that I wanted to be clear about is as we've gone through
this process, what have we been able to
restore through the insurance savings, that economically
disadvantaged one-time funding,
and then some final adjustments that happen as we go from
estimated numbers into actual people.
What we have been able to do is restore four SPTA
positions. All of these would be one year only.
That is two elementary classroom teachers, a related arts
middle school computer teacher position, and the regular
education behavior strategist role.
We also have reinstated two special education ed techs
and a custodial position.
So Madam Chair, if you'd like me to stop there and answer any questions that the
board has on positions.
Thank you. Questions?
Okay.
Member Smith.
Is the assumption that the special ed techs are not
going to be one year only, that we're going to assume that those are going to be
back next year?
That is our assumption there, and I will say that that is in
part because of our
upcoming responsibilities to Child Development Services,
and the fact that that brings new funding that persists past
this year. So again,
those we believe will be stable moving forward.
I do think
right now what's happening is the CDS transition meetings
are happening, and we're getting to know more about the population of
four-year-olds we'll be serving.
I do anticipate there could be additional positions
that we need as a result of the CDS
profile of students.
But again, those would come from a different funding source.
They would not be locally funded.
Okay. Thank you.
Any other questions?
Yes. Are there other questions? Member Richardson.
On this first page-
Yep
... I think there's a math--
Instructional strategist elementary school, you have one, but then two remain.
I think
is it two in-
I think it's because the assistant director role-
We added an instructional strategist there.
When we eliminated the second
assistant director of special education, we added
another instructional strategist to the teaching
unit.
I got you. Okay.
Multiple times I've seen occupational therapists that we have three and a half,
but now I'm seeing four.
It's actually, and again, this is positions, it's 3.8.
We have 1.8.
Oh, okay.
An employee who works-
Okay
... .8, but I'm counting it as four unique positions.
Got it.
So you're right, it's not FTEs here.
Thank you. So is it possible to
kind of understand what's changed from what you showed
us on the 13th, where we saw
a certain number of positions coming back in?
Because I think this is slightly different.
Could you just try to do the
compare and contrast between what we see here versus what you presented on the
13th?
Sure. So what we knew on the 13th
was
everything on this slide, with the exception of the related arts and the behavior
strategist. Those, if you recall, were in the
if-we-get-more-money-
Yeah
... because at that point, we had not been guaranteed.
As Abigail shared earlier, we ended up receiving about
153,000 in one-time funds for next year.
And the reason that we were able to reintroduce two teaching positions out
of that has to do with the fact that we've
gone from estimates to actuals in
some places, which means there is additional dollars
there.
When we're budgeting for sort of the average teacher, we use one number.
When we actually plug in the step and so on,
that does adjust what we've got available.
So the big change is the fact that we now are able to
reintroduce those two additional SPTA positions.
Meaning the computer science role and the behavior strategist role.
Correct.
Okay.
Which we had anticipated, but we weren't certain of.
Right. Well, it was presented as the behavior--
It was a different title. It wasn't the strategist, it was the other-
Sure. We were looking at a BCBA, and we've revisited that and are
reintroducing the behavior strategist.
Okay. That's great.
The
issue with the fact that we have no lunch aids and there was that
proposal to have bus drivers do that, that I understand
is no longer on the table. Have we figured out
who's going to be doing lunch aid work?
Sure. And as I've shared currently in
three of our elementary schools, we have not been able to
fill lunch aid positions. And so lunch duty is
done through a variety of ways.
So again, I think we'll have to look at the duty schedule.
Administrators help cover this and
meet that need, but we've got it working in other places, so.
Okay. Thanks.
Member Keller.
Just a quick clarification. Case managers in the special education detail,
those positions are filled by ed techs? Is that right?
Nope.
No. Okay.
Those are teacher positions. So case manage positions are the
lead teachers
in the classroom. So we have folks who are a resource teacher,
a composite teacher, functional life skills teacher, and then
also behavior teachers. So again, depending on
the needs of the student, the exact role
changes based on the percentage of time that a child is
with their mainstream peers versus the time that they
are participating in special education.
So those are all teaching positions.
Got it. So down here, these are
also not ed techs. So the ed techs working special education would be
addition to this?
The ed techs that work in special ed you would find, and I'm sorry you don't have
row numbers, they would be in rows 20 through
22 on the screen there.
Okay, got it.
So it's the-- What does that end up being?
88 ed tech positions in special
education next year.
Got it. Thank you.
Yep.
Other questions?
Member Holman.
No, I have a comment I'm going to make after.
Not yet. Go ahead.
Oh.
Sorry, just one last question.
Yeah, please.
Do we have any vacant special ed tech roles right
now?
I would want to--
Sorry, before I answer that question, do you mean
in this having 88 folks, would we have any
vacancies? Or do you mean-
Right. Yeah
... as of today, are there vacancies on our staff?
I
don't know. Is there a difference?
I guess I'm just trying to visualize a scenario where
I see two reduced special ed roles, ed
tech one, two, and three on row 21.
Mm-hmm.
And do we
have vacancies elsewhere such that those people that were reduced
really could be in one of those playing-- I don't know. Do you know what I mean?
Correct. Right now, within the SPESA unit,
setting aside the ed tech ones-
Yeah
... because we are not continuing with the ed tech ones.
Setting aside the ed tech ones,
all other members in that unit
would have an offer of a job next year.
Okay.
Again, it may not meet their desired position, but
they would have an offer of a position.
Thanks.
Member Keller.
Where do we end up with the bus drivers doing some
custodial work during lunches?
Through the meet and consult process, that idea wasn't viable.
So what we have done is work to restore
one custodial position to look at the--
And that position will have a little bit of a swing capacity.
In addition, there is a conversation about
standardizing some schedules to really meet building needs.
Over the last few years, there's been a little bit
moreIndividualization on schedules, and
we now really are going to have to be more refined.
And then I think the team is also working
on a real updated protocol on
cleaning expectations to make sure that it's realistic within the
time.
Great.
Yeah.
And so just to be clear, so no bus drivers will be expected to do custodial work?
Correct. That is not part of this plan.
Great. Thank you.
Member Holland.
I just actually have a comment. And I just want to say that
I just appreciate being able to see all of this.
It's very helpful. And I know there's been a tremendous amount of back and forth,
and I just want to thank you for your patience.
Any other questions?
I had a couple questions.
I'm trying to figure out, just so I can understand this, where
the
percussion
music position was. Is it in that ed tech two three
music?
Correct.
Okay. And my other question
is around the
director. So I know the director of curriculum instruction and
assessment was actually eliminated because
we
shifted that responsibility to someone else.
But if I'm correct, and correct me if I'm wrong,
the director of DEI and the assistant director of special
ed,
their title
of director was eliminated, but the position was actually
shifted to a strategist in the SPTA. Am I correct?
We have reduced all three of those positions.
And that does mean that two individuals were notified that they do not
have jobs for next year because they are non-bargaining.
They therefore, by adding the two positions down at
the bottom,
they are not eligible for those positions because there's a recall
list within SPTA and a recall provision in Article
18 that we have to go through first.
So there are three fewer directors.
You are correct that some of the work that was part of
the portfolio would be taken on by those SPTA
roles, but those two individuals would
not be in those roles.
I understand that.
Okay.
What I'm
trying to get clear is that
my understanding was that
the
removal of those titles of directors
and resulting in strategists really ended up being
cost neutral because
both of those people were willing to take coordinator positions that
would be equivalent to the strategist salary,
and I'm just trying to confirm that.
Because I-
I can confirm that they're cost neutral.
Whether or not both individuals were consulted about that, I don't know that to be
true.
Okay. Well-
But yes, I can confirm that that's cost neutral.
Okay. So,
I guess just for the sake of the public, when
we say we've eliminated 23% of directors,
we've eliminated,
correct me if I'm wrong again, we've eliminated the title of directors,
but we've just shifted the responsibilities to the
strategists
and it's cost neutral. So we haven't really saved any money.
We haven't really eliminated any position that results
in any savings in the budget. Am I correct on that?
You are correct on that, but there's three fewer directors.
Well, there's three fewer titles of directors, what you're saying.
No, I'm saying there's-
Well-
... three fewer directors.
Okay. Thank you.
Any other questions?
Okay. To finish out the presentation then,
as we think about this budget,
just thought it would be useful for the board and public to have a ten-year
look back on what has support of the school budget looked like in
this town.
I think we have heard from the public, we've heard in our
email boxes that people have concerns about the
budget.
And certainly, you can see that over the last six years,
we've experienced more than a 25% decline in our
school budget. And so I applaud the board's work to be
fiscally thoughtful as they tackle the
situation that we're in.
And I think as we look towards June 9th,
I hope we can all gather behind supporting the budget
as it moves forward and explaining that if you compare
us to surrounding districts, South Portland
has
the lowest overall operating increase that I can
find that's published right now. Other folks are still in
progress.
But again, just felt like this was important data to share
for awareness.
What I wanted to switch into is to come full circle here.
So at the beginning of the evening, you heard from some of my
colleagues about the listening session.
We've taken that through the budget process and then also wanting to bring
forward a reconfiguration roadmap on the
longer time that the board had discussed at the 13th.
What you have here is the
phases of what would this look like and what are the major
milestones that we would be seeking in
terms of the phases as we move
towards reconfiguration.The
goal of this plan and this roadmap is
that decisions would all be
concluded
by the board by November of this
year, such that we would have then a very long
implementation timeline to ensure that we are
able to give the time necessary to the meetings and the
communication and the community
building. So it sort of has us kicking off
from this listening session. I'll talk next about the steering
committee, and working in the next
months on the placement of students and staff that are
impacted by the Kahler closure,
and this budget process,
and then taking you through there.
The hope would be that we will be able to present in more detail on
this on your next regular meeting, but wanted to
give you a sense of what that roadmap looks like.
And then finally, wanted to talk about the launch of the steering committee.
We had 37 applicants for the committee.
We believe final composition will be about 20 people as
we get commitment. That composition, again,
we have board members Smith and Richardson joining.
We have family members from all five schools, teachers, ed tech, and
service represented, and administration.
And in terms of logistics,
the first two months, we are
anticipating once-a-week working group meetings.
Those will alternate between virtual and in-person, was the most popular to
accommodate
maximum participation, each of those meetings being 45
minutes.
And what we will be doing is we've reviewed the applicants and
put together an initial list.
We will be confirming people's availability,
because we do anticipate in these first two months in
particular that
it's probably two to three hours a week that someone is going to be
engaged in the work. It's not just the meetings, but it's bringing
research, it's bringing feedback, all of those pieces,
which some folks,
again, that may not be realistic for their schedule.
So invitations this week with a goal of our first meeting
next week.
And I think that brings us to,
certainly if there's questions, and then I think it's public comment.
Are there any questions? Yes, Member Holman.
Yes. Thank you for setting this out.
So
I'm talking about the
virtual and in-person. Do you see those as separate ones or hybrid?
So the group overall will be hybrid.
What we're looking at, we asked people around preference of format and before and
after school. So what we anticipate is, on the days
that it is virtual, those would be a morning meeting.
In person would be at sort of an after-school time.
So one week a virtual, one week in person seems like that
would be the best for folks.
And those in-persons, they're just in person, they're not hybrid at the time?
Correct.
Okay.
Yeah.
That's what I asked. Yeah.
That would be the goal.
Okay. Mm-hmm. And those are public meetings?
We do not anticipate them being public meetings, no.
This is an administration working committee,
so that that group can form. I think we need to make public updates
and share out notes and decisions.
But no, not public meetings.
Thank you.
Other questions? Member Fowler.
Yeah, I would just say this is a good plan, and it seems like it's
quite reactive to feedback from teachers and
families, so appreciate that.
So in May 2026, it says staff and student placement's
published. Is that the same time, I assume, that the new
attendance zones for our four elementary schools will be published?
Correct. That's specifically referencing September
of '26 placements, not what we are
planning for the reconfigured zones.
That will go through a workshopping period this summer into this
fall,
because I think that will need a lot more community
input with regards to
what variables are most important as we think about setting
the '27, '28 attendance zones.
Got it. And so for the September 1st, 2026
attendance zones, you're saying that families will know sometime in May.
Is there a specific date when the families will be notified?
We're working as quickly as possible.
And again, we know that that primarily is going to impact Kahler
families.
And so we're working as quickly as possible.
I'll bring you an update on May 8th when we get together.
Okay. Thank you.
Member Richardson.
For the May 26th-
Yep
...
staff and student placements,
are the redrawing of
boundaries going to go to the policy commit? How's that going to work?
I
think for this fall, for the Kahler students,
we may have to expedite that process because they need a new school to
attend. It's a great question. I'll talk with the chair and the policy
committee to see how we would-
Yeah
... handle the logistics of that.
Yeah, because I'm also on the policy committee and so-
Okay. For sure. Yeah
... I'm trying-
Whoever the policy-
... to visualize the timeline for that and yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Okay. Thank you. And then I had one more
question that I'm pulling up
this
Oh, the
family members from all five schools, were we able to
access
rising kindergartners or pre-K families that might
not
be in the know? Is there a way to--
And I don't want to spoil. I know you're very close to finalizing the committee
membership, but...
Sure. We definitely can go back and look at it.
It did sort of naturally distribute over the grades, but I'm
not sure that we got someone who's
not yet in the school. Maybe one child was in the school and there was
a rising child.
So, we can go back and look at that.
Yeah. It might be worthwhile to just consider that-
Sure
... vantage point.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yeah. Thank you.
Member Feller.
I apologize. I really don't want to open a can of worms here, and I fear that I am.
But when you say that the placements are going to largely
affect
Kahler students,
does that mean that the plan is just to put Kahler students in Brown
and Dyer primarily, and not say-
... there's three empty classrooms at Small, let's take some
Brown students and push them to Small, so we're not taking all the Kahler
students and just putting them into two schools.
Can you just tell me about the calculus there?
Sure. We're working through all of those models right now
to figure out.
One of the things that clearly came out of the listening session feedback
is the idea of sort of
known faces and known neighbors and staff moving
together, so balancing
that with the respect that it deserves.
Again, it may not mean that every third grader can go to the same
place, but thinking about how do we do that in the most meaningful way.
And then what we're really trying to think about is that two-year modeling, so that
we are
being aware of any potential spots where a
child or a family would be at risk for a double movement.
So,
again, too early to say exactly
where students will end up modeling through that.
But I'll just say that seems very sensible.
So you would take incoming kindergartners who are coming into
Brown for the first time, and if you need to free capacity at Brown, you take
some of those students, you bring them to Small because with reconfiguration,
they're going to be at Small anyways the next year.
So yeah, that sounds reasonable. Thanks.
Member Richardson.
Is there a plan-- I guess my assumption was I thought the steering
committee would help
form principles for those boundary drawings, but seeing how
quickly this needs to happen, is there an inflection point for
the board to agree on the guiding principles for
boundary adjustments and for redistricting
or- ... is that all just,
how do we...
Sure. Happy to bring as much of an update and more
robust
presentation to the board for your consideration.
Balancing making sure that we get all the stakeholder feedback with these families
needing to know where do they go to school next year.
So again, maybe I can work with the chair on the best process to
make sure that the board and the public is informed about that and can give
feedback.
But again, trying to also
respect people's urgency around
family planning, so.
Yeah. Maybe
we need to have a special meeting about it. I don't know.
Yeah.
I guess I had the assumption that that
is our responsibility, right? To kind of bless the boundary
redrawing.
Sure.
So having some kind of input, just information
about guidance and-
Absolutely
... everything you're saying about
what you're hoping to achieve based on the feedback makes a lot of
sense, but I think seeing it up in words, in writing,
and transparent to everybody
is a good idea.
Sounds good.
Thank you.
Questions?
Any other questions?
Okay, you want to continue?
I think that's actually, we're at public comment-
Okay
... I believe. So I'll unplug here if you want to-
No, I'm good. Thank you
... go back there, and then I'm going to log out of this computer,
too.
While you're doing that, I will read the public comment.
The board's public comment time is an opportunity for the board to listen to the
opinions of the public that relate to school and education
matters, on or off this evening's agenda.
The board is here to listen.
Anyone wishing to speak will be asked to proceed to the microphone and state your
name and the town or city where you reside.
Questions will be recorded as best as possible by the
superintendent and/or the chair and will be answered at the end
of the public comment to the extent possible.
If answers are not available,
someone will be assigned to reply to you as soon as the answer is available.
You'll be given three minutes to speak.
There will be no interaction between the public and board members.
Additionally, no clapping, booing, or other interruptive behavior will be allowed.
As a reminder, school board meetings are broadcast live, recorded, and
posted on the city's website, so please consider the impact of
your comments. Thank you. Yes.
Hi. I'm Laura Stevens, and I've worked in the school district for
27 years. I've worked at all five elementary schools, including
six years at Kahler and three years at Skillen, so I have a breadth of knowledge
about the elementary schools we have.
That's not really why I'm here. I'm here because, and I clearly didn't have a
lot of time to prepare-
When I was earning my doctorate, my minor was in
research design and statistics, and when I saw the slides
today from the 14 listening sessions, I just want to bring a few
points forward that people can consider while they're looking at that
data.
The first is there are some confounding variables in that those listening
sessions were held at different points in time in the process.
Some were held while reconfiguration was assumed to be our
path forward, and some were held after the pause was announced.
And so I think the tone of those meetings may have been different
depending on what point in the process they were held.
A second point is that the people taking notes
and conducting the questions at those meetings also varied at the
different meetings, which can affect
the information that comes out of the people who are sitting there providing the
information. So just take that into consideration.
And then finally, that the data is all subjective
data. There were no
Likert scales or tallies taken. And so I'm just curious about what
the procedure was to find those themes and surface
them out of the comments that were
made at those meetings. So those were some things about that.
Additionally, slide 27 states that
specialist educators voiced, quote, "That the current
configuration itself is the equity problem or is an equity
problem." I am one of those specialist educators in the district, and
while I know a lot of my peers do feel that way, I want you to know it's not
everybody, because I do not feel that way.
I feel that equity is a problem in our district, but I
don't necessarily believe that our configuration is leading to that equity
problem and that we could perhaps solve equity problems in different ways.
Which leads me to my final point, and that I
hope that this steering committee that's going to start meeting
will
consider a lot of options and not just
pursue the one option that has been put forward and voted
on this year. That maybe there's some
research or there's-
Pretty focused
... some other information that can impact how we move forward.
It does not necessarily have to be the one model we've talked about.
And thank you, Chair DeAngelis, for bringing up the shifts of the director
positions, because I know that's part of the conversation I've been hearing in
buildings. So thank you all for your work, and I just hope you could take those
things into consideration when you look at the data.
Thank you.
Hi. I am Sonja Croft. I'm one of the assistant directors
of instructional support.
I wanted to speak directly to the board's decision to move forward with a closed
superintendent search process. Given the level of concern around
transparency in our district right now and the transparency that you
said that you felt we didn't show you,
feels wrong. This just feels like the wrong time to limit visibility and
engagement. At this point, beyond the Zeale Consulting Group's input
sessions and thought exchange survey, no administrators,
no teachers or staff have had any direct role in this process
or any meaningfully visibility
into it.
And that absence of engagement really does matter.
It also feels really out of step with the standard practice for superintendent
searches, which typically include opportunities for candidates to meet with the
district leadership teams, engage with educators, and
also with the larger community in open forum so that we can all
provide feedback from our different perspectives.
This one session next week is not likely to allow for that quality feedback or
engagement with candidates.
These interactions are essential to making sure that it's a good fit
for not only South Portland, but for the superintendency candidate
as well.
This doesn't build trust, and it doesn't necessarily
ensure that our leader really understands the district that they're entering right
now.
The Zeale Consulting Group is a larger organization.
I noted that they are based out of Wilmington, Delaware, and I don't
know if they really understand what it means to be an educator in Southern Maine.
It's a really small town of us over here.
And we have a lot of connections in terms of understanding the
work that people can bring to the table.
I get that that might have been a recommendation,
but I think as the board, you really still hold the responsibility for the ultimate
decision of how
you led this process.
And I think that we should have had an opportunity to
have some more input.
And I think
changing that process would have showed that you really understand what this
district needs and what this community needs in this moment in time.
I know this doesn't really change anything at this point.
It's just that I think it's important for you to know that my experience with the
board in the last two years continues to be one where I think my
role, my voice-
Back to Sonja
... my input, and therefore all of the work that I've put into this district
really feels devalued and, quite frankly, irrelevant.
And that's a really hard place to be as a leader.
Thank you, Sonja.
My name is Shae Cupid, and I'm the literacy specialist at Cayler Elementary School.
I've written letters and spoken at school board meetings since early March before
any school closure or reconfiguration was voted on.
I also wrote a letter to the board right before April break regarding tonight's
vote on pausing reconfiguration for the 2026/2027
school year.
I appreciate the responses I have received from board members since I began sharing
my thoughts in early March. It reflects a deep care for our community, and
especially for our youngest learners in South Portland.
I wanted to briefly highlight some of the key points from the letter I wrote to the
board and district leadership on April 17th for those here this evening and those
listening at home. We have learned most recently that closing a school is
necessary to reach the financial stability our district needs.
However, even before school closure became part of the conversation, there was a
clear recognition that our current structure presents real challengesand
how we provide equitable programming for all students.
This led to the formation of the Boundaries and Configuration Steering Committee in
2023. The challenges we are facing with financial
sustainability and inequities across schools will still exist with the closure
of Caylor and a K to four model that does not redraw attendance
boundaries. A pause on reconfiguration does not remove these
issues. It only delays how we respond to them.
Our current structure may
unintentionally perpetuate
inequities and continue to create uneven student experiences across
schools. As I have shared before, this is not about teacher effort.
South Portland educators are deeply committed to their students.
It is about access to learning and support.
A pause can be valuable if it is used for stronger planning, clearer
communication, and meaningful collaboration.
However, there is also a concern that a pause could shift toward abandoning the
work altogether. I believe the process should be guided by purpose and
informed by a wide range of community voices.
I urge the board to remain grounded in the purpose behind this work and to be
clear, consistent, and transparent in your commitment to continuing it.
While there was strong initial support for moving forward with reconfiguration, I
understand that recent discussion has centered on extending the timeline
to allow for more intentional planning while still maintaining commitment to the
work itself.
If you are voting to extend the timeline, I hope it is paired with a commitment to
strengthen the process. Rather than a step
away from addressing inequities across our elementary schools, this year
allows us the opportunity to be a step toward an intentional
process that ensures the best conditions for student achievement and
opportunity.
In response to my most recent letter, I received thoughtful replies from
several board members.
Across those responses, I heard continued support for reconfiguration as a needed
direction-
30 seconds more
...
along with a shared emphasis on using this pause to strengthen and thoughtfully
plan the process. I also heard reassurance that there is no intention
to stop reconfiguration from moving forward, but rather to ensure it is
implemented well.
Sorry. Overall, the responses reflected both support the work,
and a desire to carry it out carefully and intentionally.
Samantha Coats here, parent and educator. I yield my time.
It has been stated that this board cannot make commitments beyond its current term.
How then will board members ensure that this pause still supports
progress toward reconfiguration for the
2027/2028 school year? With that in mind,
I leave you with these specific questions.
Number one, what are the terms of each board member?
Number two, if your term ends before the
2027/2028 school year, do you intend to run for
re-election in order to support continuity of this work?
Number three, what concrete steps will each of you take to ensure
continued progress toward reconfiguration for the
2027/2028 school year during this pause?
And number four, as the district searches for a new superintendent or
brings our candidates forward,
what expectations or questions will you bring forward
to ensure that advancing reconfiguration remains a clear
priority for their leadership?
I look forward to your responses to these questions and your continued
commitment to moving this important work forward for the benefit of our students.
Thank you.
Thank you, Shay.
Melanie.
Hi. Mindy Aloes. I'm a parent here in South Portland.
I'm here tonight with an overwhelming feeling of disappointment.
I told myself I wouldn't get involved this time, but unfortunately, I care very
deeply about our schools, our community, and our city that I've
always called home. I live within walking distance of Dyer, as
do my parents, where my kids have walked for after-school care.
The status quo benefits my family.
It would be easier for me personally if nothing
changed. I love Dyer, and I also recognize that the setup
is problematic. I benefit from the system far more than many others,
and it is because of my love for this district that I advocate for change.
When the board voted in favor of reconfiguration, I was filled with hope.
Finally, maybe our work from Boundaries and Configuration Steering Committee was
not a huge waste after all. The disparities in learning environments
across our elementary schools have been discussed for many years, decades even.
Educators know our current school configurations are a disservice to our students,
so when I hear demands for more time from staff, I am incredibly disappointed.
We've had so much time. I wish we could all model for our
students that change will be hard, but it'll be worth it, and we can do it
together. We can move forward by making progress,
not perfection. We could lessen disparities simply by combining
students who currently attend Dyer-Skillen, part of Caylor, and then
combining current students from Brown, Small, and part of Caylor.
Is this perfect? No. Is it progress? Yes.
This would ensure students within walking distance can still walk to their closest
school for three years instead of five.
This would simplify transportation needs.
I would argue that the least thought-out plan is closing Caylor without
reconfiguration. Here are my questions considering the vote to
delay.
Boundary lines being redrawn if they're only affecting Caylor
students, then that would mean that almost all of the Caylor students
would go to Brown and Skillen. So how are we going to do that without increasing
inequities at Skillen?
Will there be space for special ed classrooms when we need more grade-level
classrooms without reconfiguring?
We know reconfiguration saves money as it's more efficient use of space and
consolidation of grade-level resources.
How will you defend the more costly choice to city councilors and taxpayers,
especially considering the grant city council is offering to relieve
this year's deficit with the condition of moving forward with fiscal
responsibility?How much more will it cost to have staff moves happen
over two years instead of all at once?
How do you intend to break the endless cycle of voting to appease the most
privileged voices in our community when a vote to delay repeats that very
same pattern? And how can we trust that you will not reverse this
decision again next fall when the same vocal organized parents
return to object reconfiguration? Thank you.
Thank you, Mindy.
Good evening.
My name is Sarah Collins, and I'm a parent of two students at Dyer as well as an
educator.
I wish Mindy and I had talked beforehand, because we have a lot of the same points.
But as we discuss a delay, I want to start by acknowledging
something honestly, because it's how I've been feeling, and it's something
that many families have felt. There's a part of me that
feels relief at the idea of a delay, relief that we won't have to rush through a
major transition, relief that my children will have some continuity next year.
I also feel relief that the dominant messaging tonight from the district and from
the school board is still a plan to move towards reconfiguration.
But alongside that relief, I have a deep sense of concern
because what's being called a delay risks becoming something else, a
step away from reconfiguration altogether without a clear plan for how we
address the inequities we all know exist in our district.
This conversation didn't start this year.
As a district, we've been talking about inequity for a long time.
And as was said in the Dyer listening session, sometimes it is more painful to
stretch change out over years than it is to move forward with intention.
I also want to acknowledge what I'm hearing from others, from families of students
with special needs who are worried about losing consistency, from educators who are
reeling from staffing cuts and uncertainty, and from families who are asking for
clarity about what this will mean for their children.
Those concerns are real, and they deserve to be heard.
At the same time, I think we have to be equally honest about something else.
The inequities between our schools are real.
When some classrooms have 13 students and others have over 20, that is not
equity. When access to programs and services varies widely between
schools, that's not equity. And when some students experience
stability and proximity while others face greater disruption, that's not
equity. And right now, the burden of this decision is not being
shared equitably. The Caylor community is being asked to carry the weight
of change largely on their own, losing their school, their community, and their
sense of stability while many other schools, including my own, appear at
this point to remain relatively unchanged.
As we delay reconfiguration, that imbalance only deepens.
The most meaningful way to support the Caylor community would have been to not
prolong uncertainty but to move forward together so that that change was shared and
so that all students could benefit from a more equitable system.
I say this with care because I'm part of a community that benefits from some of
these advantages. My children have thrived at Dyer.
We love our school, our teachers, and our neighborhood.
But loving the school and our neighborhood and committing to the well-being of our
entire district should not be in conflict.
If anything, it asks more of us.
It asks us to recognize that meaningful change is often uncomfortable-
30 seconds left
... and that that discomfort alone is not a reason to stop.
So if the board chooses to delay this decision, I urge you, do not let this become
a quiet step away from that goal. Continue the work, provide
a clear timeline, engage the community in a transparent and inclusive
process, and keep equity, not comfort, at the center of the
decision. I love the school in my neighborhood, and I love this
community. I believe we're capable of making decisions that honor both.
Thank you.
Glad.
Hello, my name is Vladimir Korshin. I'm a parent at Small school.
And my comments this evening presume that the board will vote to pause
reconfiguration this evening.
Proceeding at this point, given everything that we have learned and, more
importantly, everything we still don't know, would be completely irresponsible,
bordering on negligent. My greatest issue with this entire
process is that reconfiguration is not an ideology to be first
imposed and then later sold. It is a policy that should be
evaluated thoroughly and impartially.
If the case for reconfiguration is strong, the community will buy in,
and the way to confirm that buy-in is with a vote.
That should all sound very reasonable.
However, I've had conversations with multiple high-profile reconfiguration
advocates who tell me that we should not bring this issue to a vote
because voters are prejudiced or uninformed.
That is deeply condescending and undemocratic.
To address the issue of prejudice, there appears to be a misconception that people
opposed to reconfiguration are either outwardly or implicitly racist or classist.
I'll speak for myself, but I feel comfortable representing the vast majority of
people in our camp who believe that the quality of human character is distributed
evenly across ethnic groups and income levels.
Having lived most of my life in highly diverse communities, I unequivocally
welcome greater diversity into South Portland and into Maine broadly.
If reconfiguration were free, I would likely endorse it. But it is not free.
It is not free because it requires that we take our youngest children, including
kindergartners and first graders who currently walk to school with their parents
and friends, and instead bus them some unknown distance.
It is not free because every year a student spends at the same school environment,
they grow more comfortable and more confident.
Yet under reconfiguration, South Portland students would transition schools five
times in their first 10 years.
And it is not free because it is literally not free.
It costs taxpayers money, money that could go instead to teachers or ed techs who
actually do the teaching.
Most strangely of all, we would be paying for something that we already have.
All South Portland students already learn together in fifth, sixth,
seventh, eighth, ninth, tenth, eleventh, and twelfth grades.
The benefits, to the extent that they are real, are built into the
system.Whatever incremental theoretical gains
cannot be worth the immense cost to the community, walkability, and budget.
30 seconds.
So I end this with a question to each of you.
Will the community have a chance to vote on reconfiguration before it is
implemented? Why or why not? Please go on the record with your
reasoning and avoid excuses related to procedure, as we know that the board is
well-positioned to recommend a vote to city council.
If you do not support a vote, what recourse do you recommend for the large
number of community members that remain skeptical about reconfiguration? Thank you.
Thank you, Vlad.
Hi.
My name is Aiden Renahan. I'm a parent of a Brown kindergartner and a
future kindergartner.
So I emailed all of you earlier today, so I'm going to repeat some of my
comments for the public. First of all, I want to thank Abigail for the amazing
amount of work she did on the budget process and how trans-
Can you get closer to the mic, please? I'm sorry.
Yeah. I want to publicly thank Abigail for the work she did on the budget process
and the transparency and clarity she's brought to this.
This was an incredibly hard process for everybody.
The decisions that got made, I think, are going to be felt for a long time.
But I genuinely worry that with the budget, we're doing a victory lap when the hard
work is yet to come. So we're entering a budget
year next year where we have somewhere between $179 and
$465,000 in contingency
funds. That's between a .2 and .6% total
amount. So a budget is not reality.
A budget is a plan to address reality.
I want to emphasize that. And it is going to take an incredible amount of
hard work to deal with the reality of what the FY27 budget means.
Now, I want to publicly thank city council for their offer to wipe the
deficit clean. I think it was an incredible gift that they gave us.
But I think it was a gift that was clear.
It's a gift to allow us to start fresh and to begin anew, and to find the financial
stability that Abigail is talking about, that she said, the finance director said,
would take years for us to achieve.
And so I would argue that FY27 should be
focusing on finding efficiencies, finding top-line revenue
opportunities, finding ways that we can put this district on a stable footing.
And yet I sit here and I read the motion and the presentation and the
roadmap around reconfiguration, and I don't hear cost mentioned
once. I don't hear the financial plan mentioned
once. The lack of financial planning is what has put this
district into the position we are in and has made this FY27 process
so challenging. And I worry that we are doing what we have done in the past.
We are taking the short-term decisions we have made, declaring that
we are done, and moving on to programmatic changes without building fiscal
discipline and fiscal responsibility into all the decisions we make moving
forward. Fiscal discipline and responsibility is what this board
and this district owe to the taxpayers to stop the erosion of voter
support on the budget, and it has to be a part of the reconfiguration
process. Now, I am totally open to the idea that reconfiguration
can be a core part of the financial stability of this district moving forward.
30 seconds.
But that has to be explored and aligned.
It cannot be a silent reason. So here are my questions.
What is the district's confident estimate today that we will end FY27 without a
deficit? What is the district's plan if we accrue a budget deficit at the end of
FY27? Can each of the board members answer whether or not they believe
budget savings or resource efficiency are a reason to pursue reconfiguration?
Will you commit to providing a clear budget for the reconfiguration process that
outlines costs and compares that budget against keeping the status
quo or redoing changing boundaries in a K through
four model? And will budget planning be considered in the design and
implementation of reconfiguration for FY28?
And will an FY27 operating budget change our approach
or consideration of implementing
reconfiguration if we find ourselves in this situation? Thank you.
Thank you.
Hi, school board members. I appreciate the opportunity to speak to you tonight.
My name is Victoria Libby. I'm a South Portland resident with one child in
elementary school and another who will be entering soon.
These past few months have been dizzying, to say the least,
and destabilizing.
And yet, I do see one silver lining.
Our community has woken up.
It's woken up to the need for engagement.
Families are now paying attention. They're asking thoughtful questions.
They're showing up because they deeply care about the future of our schools.
And we are disturbed by the timeline of events.
We are watching the rapid closure of Cayler,
giving the families and staff of that school minimal time to prepare.
We've seen sweeping student-facing staff cuts
without clear explanation for why that's justified above upper
administrative
staff cuts. And now we're being asked to consider widespread elementary
reconfiguration within a few months without a clear plan,
cost-benefit analysis, or evidence of how this is going to benefit
our children.
Like I said, the community is engaged and we're ready.
If nothing else, we're deeply aware of the issues in our schools now in a way
that we were not before, and that's a good thing because there's a lot of
energy now wanting to find ways to address those issues.
So
you have an opportunity
to harness this energy and use it to bring us together, or
you risk fracturing this community more.
Your own data shows that staff and families share serious concerns.
The timeline feels rushed. There's a need for more clarity in planning,
and there's concern for our youngest and most vulnerable students.
When the people closest to our children are telling us that this pace is
too rushed, we need to listenIf those
concerns are acknowledged and acted on, this can be the beginning of a
stronger, more collaborative relationship between the school board and the
community. But if the feedback you've collected is not meaningfully
incorporated, you risk losing this engagement.
And that would be a loss not just for families, but for the long-term strength of
our schools.
On top of all that, we're being asked to do this in a matter of months,
what other districts have taken years to plan.
Nearby communities like Scarborough and Gorham have approached reconfigurations
as multi-year processes with time for study, feedback, and adjustment.
Even here in South Portland, our middle school consolidation took-
30 seconds left
... years of planning and community engagement.
That contrast matters.
This timeline matters. So as you consider a pause tonight, I
urge you to see an opportunity. It's an opportunity to show this community you're
listening, an opportunity to act on the concerns you've gathered,
an opportunity to build trust with a community that wants to be part of the
solution.
In the immediate, let's focus on supporting Caylor families, ensuring a thoughtful
transition, and a real sense of belonging in their new schools.
That's three minutes.
And then altogether, let's take the time to thoughtfully and transparently
plan for the future. Thank you.
Thank you, Victoria.
Good evening. Sarah Gay, parent, teacher, and president of the South
Portland Teachers Association.
I wasn't planning to speak. You can put that one on your bingo cards.
But I agreed with every word that Sonia Croft shared
in her comment.
We, in a number of different configurations of comments from
different members of our team, indicated some serious concern
about the lack of stakeholder involvement in the superintendent search process
several months ago and were told then that that was a
selling point of working with Zeal, and that that was their
insistence. And I just would like to name that
I think that needs some explanation, and there needs to be a little more
disclosure from the board about why that was a process that was agreed
to.
And the other just quick thing, driving over this afternoon, I
was leaving a parent-teacher conference that was really actually one of the better
conversations I've had in a while.
And I was thinking, just had the pit of my stomach like, "I know I'm walking into
something that is going to feel hard, really hard." And I think
I'm underselling.
It doesn't have to be this way. And
I think I really appreciate the comments that folks have made about how this is an
opportunity to regain trust, to reframe
really how we value each other. And I think that sense of
value is something I hear my colleagues question and worry
about every day is, "Are we valued enough for our voices to truly matter?"
And I think we have a chance to demonstrate that they do.
I hope they do. So, thank you.
Thank you, Sarah.
Abby.
Hi. Abby Anderson, SPTA vice president,
one of three.
I just have a few questions tonight.
The first question, it seems like we could get an answer to tonight, which would
be lovely. So, how are the shifts
for the DEI and assistant special ed directors cost
neutral if they would go to a teacher in the SPTA unit?
We learned last year through the budget process what the salaries were for these
director-level positions, and both salaries were over the maximum
level on our pay scale for our unit.
And it's my understanding that the director-level positions do receive a benefits
package as members of our unit do.
I'm sure coverage is different somehow.
I'm just struggling to understand how there could be cost neutrality when our top
salary scale is tens of thousands of dollars under the salary for some of
those directors. So clearly, I'm missing something.
Would love to have clarity on that.
Another question that I think could be answered tonight is what
is the anticipated cost of the Curriculum Council compared to the
current salary of the curriculum of instruction and
assessments director and the current curriculum stipends?
And a follow-up, do we know how this council will function?
The following question, I'm okay if that's answered at a later date.
How will the unions be included in the reconfiguration
planning process?
So those are my questions. Next is just a pitch to the
public to please vote in the June referendum.
I did some number crunching, and in
2024, we had
6.7 of South Portland registered voters cast a ballot in the June
referendum. Last year, in 2025, we had 12.6%.
The highest turnout in the last decade was around a third, so
33%. Please vote. We are fortunate to
live in a state where voting is very accessible, so please
take advantage of that. Voting is how you can say I love you to your community,
even if you don't get what you want.
You can register to vote online or at the city clerk's office, or the day of
at your polling place.
If you can't get there on the voting day in June, you can vote by mail, or you can
just go into City Hall and cast a ballot. Everyone will help you.
You can email anyone on this board. You can email me.
You can email-
30 seconds
... anyone in South Portland that works here, and we will help you register and
figure out where to go.
If you're watching this meeting, I know I'm preaching to the choir.
But please encourage your neighbors, friends, family to vote
and support the school budget. Maybe I'm just talented at this because I'm a
youngest child, but be annoying about it.
Remind them multiple times. We need you to turn out for us.
So, thank you.
Thank you, Abby. Bethany.
Hi, Bethany Connolly, principal at Skillen.
I'm speaking tonight from multiple perspectives, building
principal, South Portland Administrators Association president,
and as someone who cares deeply about this community that I have served for the
past nine years.
While the announcement regarding the meet and greet for the superintendent
finalists was shared at the beginning of this meeting, and earlier this
evening via email to the community, I first heard this update from
information shared at the city council meeting last night.
To be transparent, I was not actually watching or in attendance at the
council meeting, but I did receive some text messages from
people who were asking, "Did you know about this?" I
did not. Not as a building principal, not as an
association president, not as a leader in this district.
How is this possible, given this is a process our school board
is leading? Our school board, who time and again
demand more transparency, more stakeholder engagement,
and more opportunities for all voices to be heard.
As I looked for answers to this question, I went back to the district webpage
about the superintendent search and discovered a dearth of information.
While there is information from Zeal and lists of past dates and times for
staff and family input sessions, other than the leadership profile
from Zeal, there is very little helpful, transparent, and
useful information about this process.
So I went back to the December 10th workshop and listened to the Zeal
presentation, during which Jeff Melendez shared that the board
is the primary decision-maker and the only hiring decision the
board makes,
saying that he would not abdicate this decision to anyone.
He went on to say that the school board superintendent relationship
is the most important and critical relationship in the school system.
So important, in fact, he, and I quote, "Can't imagine it
not being done by you." It being hiring, you being the board.
I have heard these statements referred to by Chair DeAngelis as the
rationale for the closed process of hiring a superintendent.
This led me down another path in search of more clarity and understanding of
how this process has played out thus far.
Over the past several years, there have been many superintendent searches
conducted by districts throughout the state of Maine, so I did a little
research and investigated how those searches were conducted.
Of the six districts I looked at, including Portland, Falmouth, Yarmouth,
RSU 21, MSAD 28, and MSAD
15, to a district, every process included a
committee of stakeholders that were included.
Some were called screening committees, others search committees, but all included
representatives from all stakeholder groups, including teachers,
building and district level administrators, support staff,
association representatives, parents and community members,
and board members. Some districts included extensive
biographies for each member of the search committee that outlined their connection
to the school district and the expertise they bring to the process.
The role of these committees varied among the districts.
Some screened applicants and made recommendations to the board of who to interview.
Others selected finalists to be interviewed, and one
participated in the interviews themselves.
Regardless, the final hiring decision in all of these districts
was made, as it should be, by the school board.
The process I found most interesting was the recent search done by
the Yarmouth School Department, who also contracted with Zeal.
In Yarmouth, the search committee consisted of four board members, three
administrators, one from each level, elementary,
middle, and high school, three teachers from each level,
and two community members who are also parents of students across the three
levels. As I reviewed the process Yarmouth completed with
Zeal as the executive search firm, I questioned why our
process in South Portland includes only the board and no
other stakeholders. I recognize that Zeal hosted a variety
of input sessions for staff and community in South Portland.
This was also done in Yarmouth. I also know that at the
combined staff and community session hosted at Skillen-
30 seconds, Bethany
... three people were in attendance.
At the virtual staff session offered on February 3rd, there were
zero staff in attendance.
I know this does not represent the level of engagement and opportunity for input
that this board has said it values.
Not including any stakeholders, association leadership, teachers,
support staff, parents, or community members on a search or
screening committee was at best a missed opportunity,
and at worst, shows a complete lack of regard for the-
Three minutes
... very transparency-
Allison Hopkins, principal of Dyer. I yield my time.
Thank you
... a complete lack of regard for the very transparency and
engagement this board purports to value.
Just because Zeal recommended a closed process does not mean that the board had to
follow that recommendation. Including stakeholders in a
process does not take the responsibility of hiring the superintendent
away from the board. Rather, it would have demonstrated the board's and
district's commitment to collaboration and transparency.
I want to recognize that I'm somewhat late to the party here.
I do not expect that my comments will result in any change.
However, I felt compelled to speak because if I, as a district
administrator and association leader, am lacking
information and clarity around the superintendent search process and
timeline, I imagine other stakeholders in this community are as
well.
With everything that is happening in our community and school district over the
past few months, and continues to be prolongedI
fear that this process
is mirroring the dynamics I see happening at the national level.
When a challenging and complex issue arises over here,
another emerges over there, limiting our capacity to monitor and
respond thoughtfully to all that is happening.
I'm disappointed that the board has devalued the input and engagement of
leaders, teachers, support staff, and the community in the important
process of choosing the next superintendent of South Portland.
Thank you, Anne.
Hi, my name is Alex Strube, and I'm a parent in South Portland School
District.
Good evening. I want to start by thanking the board.
The option to pause the proposal on reconfiguration gives our district something
badly that it needed, which is time.
But now the question is: how do we use that time?
In 2024, the Boundaries and Configurations Committee did real work on our behalf.
They produced clear, concrete recommendations for the path forward.
These options included engaging a consultant to complete an
impact study of potential grade-level configuration changes, including
resources and traffic implications.
Also included securing meaningful family input and reviewing highly
successful magnet programs in other districts.
It also included engaging a consultant to develop a proposal for a controlled
choice model,
and then to present these findings to the board on a defined timeline.
The committee called these the most viable long-term solutions that address
our needs as a community. That work was paused, and this
year gives us a chance to complete it.
I want to acknowledge the real tension this board now holds.
We have Kaylor families who need stability, clarity, and care through their
transition.
And we have a district-wide question of equity that deserves a thoughtful,
evidence-based answer rather than a rushed one.
Both of these things matter, and neither should be sacrificed for the other.
So my questions to the board are offered in that spirit.
How will you ensure Kaylor students, families, and staff experience a stable,
well-supported transition this year, while simultaneously using this
time to complete the boundaries and configurations work that the district committed
to?
Will you revisit that 2024 proposal, the impact study, the consultant
engagement, the family input process, and the review of comparable models,
so that when we return to reconfiguration, we return with evidence,
community trust, and a real plan?
And then other than the Reconfiguration Steering Committee, how can parents engage
meaningfully in larger conversations around our schools, things such
as investments in art, computer science,
other than simply just attending to public comment?
Rushing this forward risks the very progress that we all want, and taking this year
to plan it meaningfully, it well protects it.
I'm grateful for your leadership, and I'm asking that we use this year fully.
Thank you.
Thank you, Alex. Julia.
Good evening, board.
This is a bummer. My name's Julia Edwards.
I live on Dawson Street. I have a child at Skillen
and a child who's yet to be in the district.
I just would like to hear from each of the board members, if you would
indulge me and those watching who can't be here tonight.
There are many, because they're texting me furiously.
I need to understand how, if a budget is a
representation of values,
how removing an expert whose sole job
is to infuse equity, diversity,
inclusion, and belonging into everything from the top
down at a leadership level, how
removing that position in light of everything that we are about to engage
in on now an extended timeline, possibly not ever,
whatever the community does, we need somebody who has this
expertise. We do not have it
if we do not have this position. And I do not know how we can
put ourselves out to the public and say we are going to engage in
reconfiguration and make this about actually achieving or trying to achieve
equity and unraveling the strands of systemic racism that have been
here for generations,
and not have somebody whose sole job is to handle those things.
So I'm really frustrated that
linkage hasn't been made publicly by...
I think tonight was the first time I'm hearing it. Thank you, Chair DeAngelis.
But it should've been part of the conversation
from the jump. And the idea of that position just sort
of sailing away into
a position of not
the opposite of leadership that has some authority,
and might I add, the only person of color in the administration, that's
problematic to me. If we're going into this next phase
with
a goal of bringing people together and doing the work
justice,
then where's the resources to back that up?
I'm really
concerned about that. So I would like to understand and get some assurance from all
of you beyond just we trust our leadership and we trust that... No.
I need to know how this position, the DEI coordinator, not even
being a consideration to bring back and restore, is
going to do justice to the work of reconfiguration that needs to happen.
30 seconds.
I realize that. Thank you. I also feel like Groundhog Day because three years
ago, the work started for boundaries and configurations in 2023.
It took about a year and a half.
Almost every time I spoke, I asked where is the effort to bring in
families that are not yet in the district.
And so, I would like to reiterate that question, and I would like to
just have that thought about, because most of us in this room probably won't
really have to engage too much
inBy the time things come around
to engage in the results of what happens with reconfiguration or not.
But the families whose kids aren't here-
That's three minutes
... will have to do that. So I'd like to know what's going to be done to reach
them. Thank you.
Thank you, Julia.
Hi, my name is David Fullerton. I'm a resident of South Portland.
I have a daughter in first grade and a three-year-old son that will be in
kindergarten in a couple years.
I recently attended a listening session facilitated by a member of the
administration.
During this dialogue, they shared that they had been a part of a successful
reconfiguration in another school district similar to what is being proposed in
South Portland. They stated that it had gone well and members of the community were
glad they did it in the end, despite the pain of the process.
After the meeting, I was kicking myself for not asking what was this school
district. Well, I decided to do some research.
Come to find out it is MSAD58. That's
actually the school district I grew up in.
I attended King Field Elementary School, Mount Abraham High School, and continue to
have strong connections to the area, and I'm here to share that this
reconfiguration has not been a success.
I know that MSAD58 and South Portland are, they're not the same.
MSAD58 is a massive rural district covering 500 square miles,
South Portland, much smaller urban city.
But the core of what they did is identical to being what's proposed here.
They abandoned traditional neighborhood schools to shift to a grade
banded sister school model on a rushed timeframe, and the
result was not a success. It alienated parents, fractured community,
and destroyed public trust. Voters routinely began
rejecting annual operating budgets.
Towns felt so ignored and abused by the district's management that
the three primary towns that make up the district, Strong, Phillips, and Kingfield,
have voted to begin the formal legal process to withdraw from the district
entirely. MSAD58 in all likelihood will not continue to
exist. Now, I acknowledge that this rural
community has enrollment and budget issues that
may have been insurmountable either way.
Regardless, I find it interesting that it was sold to me as a success story when it
simply isn't any by any stretch of the imagination.
It did not solve the long-term problems that people were told it would.
It is also clear to me how important public support is.
If you want this to work, you need public buy-in or you risk the whole thing
coming undone in a few years. We cannot afford to replicate what happened with
MSAD58. South Portland thrives on the strength of its neighborhood
schools. To dismantle them without localized research proving
it will yield better outcomes for our children is a massive irresponsible risk.
I urge the board to pause on reconfiguration.
To be clear, I can be persuaded to support
reconfiguration, put together a comprehensive plan and explain how this
is going to work, listen to the feedback of the community, and take a
look at what happened with MSAD58 with their rushed reconfiguration.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, David.
Meredith Diamond, community member, parent, educator.
Rosemary, I'm using my public comment tonight to invite you to act in
service to the wellbeing of our schools and community by resigning from your
position on the South Portland School Board.
Reflecting on the events of the past two months, I'm not sure that you can see the
impact of your words and deeds.
While you may not have intended these impacts, they are real and lasting.
You have been a member of this board since 2022.
You have had an up-close view of and an active role in the decision-making that
created this acute financial crisis.
In the past two months alone, you have shepherded this district through a budget
development process that has generated more fear, division,
animosity, and hurt than any community should be expected to bear.
I did not understand the district's financial situation when I began attending
meetings, but I quickly learned that I wasn't the only one.
In a March meeting, you rebuked participants in public comment for referencing a
deficit. "We don't have a deficit," you said, but you offered no
explanation for the financial stress the district is obviously
experiencing.
Weeks later, we learn that there is deep concern that we are
facing an FY26 deficit that could be as high as $2
million. Either you were confused, unaware,
or misleading. None of these demonstrates the leadership we
need. On March 23rd, in one of the most
charged and protracted meetings we've had during this process, you used the
power of your position to elevate your own story over all of the other
stories in the room.
Over the stories of teachers who had just learned they'd be losing their jobs,
over the stories of kids suddenly afraid that their school might close,
over the stories of families whose ways of life in this community felt suddenly
vulnerable to the decisions of the board you
lead. You have waged a campaign that you describe
as a pursuit of equity without first identifying what you
mean when you talk about equity or clarifying how the initiatives you're
pushing will help us achieve it.
You either failed to hear or willfully ignored the community's repeated
pleas for transparency, and instead engineered a superintendent
hiring process that is an essential blackout and which
defies statewide norms that emphasize the importance of collective
input on this critical decision.
You led the board deliberation about closing an elementary school.
This began with a district suggestion that Skillen be closed, but this
suggestion was dismissed immediately by you and other board members, reflecting a
failure of your duty to coordinate with the superintendent regarding budget
proposals.
30 seconds.
Subsequent proposals that either Dyer or Keller be closed created confusion
and whiplash citywide. In the final vote to close Keller, you
surprised everyone in the room by voting no, but then offered no
explanationYou have chaired multiple executive sessions
that one board member described as creating a quote, "untenable, unprofessional
environment."
Something about these meetings was so egregious that this board member resigned as
a result.
At a meeting the next day, you began not by addressing the member's conspicuous
absence or the community's growing list of grievances-
Three minutes.
Sam Dimon, yield my time
...
the community's growing list of grievances, but by chiding your constituents for
the tone of our commentary at previous meetings.
"The disrespect, the tone, it crossed a line," you said, before emphasizing that
empathy and kindness are what you expect to hear from your hurt and frustrated
community.
Later, you used an interview with "The Press Herald" to lament that you had been
singled out and publicly shamed. You shared that you were experiencing many
sleepless nights as a result of this.
What you didn't do was use this opportunity to recognize the trauma and
anger reverberating across our community.
Opening another meeting in crisis with a 10-minute seminar on civility
directed at the constituents you are supposed to serve is not respectful,
empathetic, or kind leadership. This is fragility and backward
framing. This is an elected leader forgetting that her responsibility is to
model empathy and kindness for the hurt and vulnerable who feel ignored.
This is the silencing of dissent by labeling it mean and hateful.
In a recent listening session hosted by Eleni and Claire, you
attended, but not alongside your fellow board members.
Instead, you fueled community division by sitting in the audience, participating
as a speaker rather than a listener, and even swearing at a fellow board member to
emphasize your disagreement.
A school board chair has responsibilities that a private citizen does not.
The position is charged with real power over the lives of children, families,
educators, and staff. Anyone who asks to be trusted with this
power is obligated to absorb criticism without centering their own
feelings, to engage with hard questions rather than managing
the people asking them, and to treat transparency as a baseline
standard rather than a threat.
In responding to a community crisis by spotlighting your own feelings,
you have shown us that it's your own hurt and not the hurt in your community that's
keeping you up at night.
I recognize, Rosemary, that you have served this community in many roles.
I am also asking you to recognize that you are not the leader that South
Portland schools needs right now.
We need a new way forward, and that requires a leader who will absorb criticism
with grace, treat frustration as data rather than disruption,
and build trust rather than destroy it.
You have taught us that this is not leadership you can provide.
Please give us the gift of stepping aside so that someone else can.
Thank you, Meredith.
Hi. My name's Anna. I live in South Portland.
I have a kid at Kayler,
a first grader,
and
I have sent a couple of emails to the board,
and some of you have gotten back to me, some of you have not.
Rosemary has spent
probably an hour and a half on the phone with me.
She called me two minutes after I sent my email, which I thought was really
amazing,
and listened to what I had to say. And I don't know.
I would be sad to see you resign personally.
I think you offer a valuable
service, and I'm grateful for you, and I just want to publicly say
thanks.
And also, I know that there are
teachers and staff in the district who support
reconfiguration and are afraid to come forward and say that because
it's tense and crazy,
which sucks. It just sucks. I don't know that it's the best thing.
I don't think anybody does know that it is or isn't, but I do feel
scared that--
Again, I have a first grader. I'm new to this
conversation. But as I've talked to people who
in the schools who know, this is not a new conversation.
Nobody is saying it's not a rushed timeline. It is. That's obvious.
But I think we could totally do it.
Is it going to be sloppy, and is it going to require
tweaking? Of course.
Nothing that's happening is perfect.
But I just feel like it's kicking the can down the road
to rescind that vote, and it's giving
just more time to the people who want it to never
happen.
That I do believe, and
that breaks my heart. So
I know you guys have all been working 3,000 hours, and I'm grateful for all of you,
but Rosemary, thank you so much.
Thank you very much, Anna.
Hi, I'll make this quick. Alexander Donegan, South Portland resident, and I have
a five-year-old who's going to go into kindergarten.
Push the mic a little bit up so it'll work for you.
Hi. Alexander Donegan, South Portland resident, parent of a five-year-old about to
go into kindergarten. We were districted for Kayler.
All of a sudden, that's not happening, and now there's reconfiguration, but now
I'm just getting whiplash. I just want to
know if we are postponing,
what everyone's going to do to make it so
incoming students aren't going to
switch multiple times. And
if they are,
what steps were taken to try to avoid that?
But I know we can't make everyone happy, but it's already a lot
to have your first kid go into kindergarten for the first time, so
any guidance on that would be great. Thank you.
Thank you, Alexander. Jen.
Hi, my name's Jennifer Marshall. I am a resident of South
Portland.
I am the president of the service employees.
I wasn't planning on talking tonight, but
I agree with what Sarah Gay said, and Bethany.
I was kind of shocked tonight when I saw the email about the superintendent.
As the president of the service employees,
typically we're a part of the process.
I know past presidents have been in all the unions.
If not all of us, I want some of us
to find out at the same time as the public about certain things.
The transparency's not there, and I just want you
aware. I agree with, especially Bethany, you said it way better than I could've,
but
you have to understand how strongly we feel. We want to be a part of the process.
Another thing is, most of you in a few years, you won't be
sitting there. Most of us will still be here.
We're the ones that will have to work with the superintendent if we're still
presidents or leaders or whatever.
So
it's really shocking that we weren't part of this process.
And as far as the bus drivers,
they really appreciate that that was taken off the table, and the ones that
had changed plans to leave the district have changed their
plans back to stay. So thank you very much for that.
Have a good night.
Thank you, Jennifer.
Ishmael.
My name is Ishmael Daniels, Caylor parent.
I'm actually kind of disappointed
that people are taking this time, their three minutes,
to use Caylor as a crutch.
Saying that you care about our school
and that reconfiguration should be paused to take
time sounds like BS.
You didn't care when they were voting to close our school.
You've never been to our school.
Some of you have made comments about a meeting that happened at our school that you
weren't even at.
It seems disingenuine.
Caylor parents have dealt with the fact that our school is closed.
We've dealt with it. We've accepted it.
We took it on the chin.
We weren't happy about it, but we had to make that decision to keep the kids happy
and keep them going to school.
Coming up here and saying that reconfiguration should be reconsidered
because it hurts your butt
is BS.
Pausing reconfiguration
is a spit in our face.
Full on.
You guys made a decision.
You cut us.
We took it.
We stitched it.
Stick to it.
We got little kids to deal with.
We don't want to deal with this next year.
We don't want to fill this room again.
You made a decision. It sucked.
It hurts.
We're adults.
Who cares what these people say?
You guys have a responsibility to stick to what you said.
Stick to it.
Reconfigure.
Reconfigure. We got to get it done.
If you put it on somebody else's hands,
you change the superintendent, you change the staff,
what does that do?
That's like me giving you my bills. It ain't going to happen, right?
Make it happen. Please. Make it happen.
Make it happen. We know who voted.
It's public. Just make it happen. But don't listen to these people out here talking
about, "Oh, poor Caylor."
They don't care.
That's BS.
Do what's right, please.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ishmael.
My name is Amy. I'm a South Portland resident and another Caylor parent, and I want
to echo what Ishmael has said, my fellow PTA parent, has
said that the we're here to support Caylor and welcome everybody with open
arms, and the rhetoric that I've been hearing does feel very disingenuous from
everybody because it just feels like largely nobody really cares about the Caylor
kids. Because if they did, they would listen to reconfiguration a little bit
better, listen to the pros of it instead of immediately saying it's not the right
thing to do, and to kick it down for another year, so again, we're all here making
the same arguments again.
Rosemary, thank you so much for calling me the minute I wrote my email to you.
That was really great to have that time to speak with you.
And if we're going to encourage people to rethink their positions here
and how they lead us, I think a lot of people need to rethink how they
have behaved during this entire time.
Because the things I've seen on social media has been classist.
The things that have been
said about Caylor, calling them tank kids, all these different
things, has been horrible. Leaving threatening voicemails to a member of the
board is disgusting behavior. So if we're asking for somebody to
rethink how she is on the board, I think a lot of people need to rethink how they
have behaved these last few months, because honestly, I will not look at this
community the same after this.
Thank you.
Thank you, Amy.
If no further public comments- ... public comment is closed.
Thank you.
And we are at the consideration and action to
approve the consent agenda below.
The only item on the consent agenda is to-
We don't have to answer questions?
I'm sorry.
We don't have to answer questions.
Oh, I'm sorry. Thank you,
Claire.Appreciate that.
We're going to
do our best to see if we can answer public
questions. So somebody can keep
me
abreast here. There were some comments
that were
asking about the terms of board
members. Do we intend to run for re-election?
And
the
terms of board members are all posted on the city
website, so you can see that. I don't know whether anybody
wants to speak about whether they plan to run for re-election.
That's individual choice,
if people want to talk about that. And this person also asked
what concrete steps will we take. I think it was what concrete steps will we
take to ensure that
reconfiguration goes forward.
These are really for any board member to respond because these
are questions to board members. So,
as I said, terms of office are posted on the city website.
If people want to talk about when their board term is up and whether they
plan to run for re-election,
I'll start there. Does anybody want to speak to that?
Member Feller.
Sure. My term is up in 2028. Am I going to
run for re-election?
I don't know. Probably.
Let's see. What concrete steps will each of you take to ensure progress towards
reconfiguration? I think we're taking a pretty concrete step
tonight in voting for a resolution
that commits to implementing reconfiguration in 2027.
What expectations do you have for the new superintendent?
We expect that the new superintendent is going to be excited to implement
reconfiguration.
And
that is something that I think everyone on this board is
using to evaluate superintendent candidates.
Are you on board with what this community has largely said, which is that we want
to reconfigure our elementary schools?
Anybody else like to respond?
Okay.
We had some questions.
Also, the next set of questions I have, and somebody can jump in if
I'm not getting these all.
But
the next question was,
I think, again, was about
reconfiguration and about how individuals
are going to... First question was: how are we going to
break the pattern of supporting the pattern of
what was referenced as privileged
parents?
Does anybody want to respond to that?
I think that's an unfair question.
I don't want to identify parents as privileged or unprivileged.
I think that's part of our work is to
try to neutralize some of that divide that's going
on right now, particularly right now in this room and in our
community.
I
think the most important mechanism we can
use to engage with our community is
information on
and being able to answer questions,
pretty basic questions about a plan, and we have not been able to provide answers
to those questions.
And I
don't think that's unreasonable, guys. I just don't.
I'm sick to my stomach right now.
I feel like
each and every one of us is really doing the best that we can in a really, really
impossible situation. And
hindsight's 20/20 on a lot of things.
Yes, a closed superintendent process looks real crappy right now.
Okay? It really does not look good.
And that's why we did what we did to
invite the community to meet the two finalists next week.
I
think
we're all doing the best that we can with this situation and
having to deal with a budget that cut $8 million and 70 plus
staff. None of us asked for this situation.
We all wanted
to do what's best for our community.
And
so it's really
uncomfortable to start to think about have we-- no, we have
not listened to privileged voices.
The voices that were against reconfiguration, those are the
same voices that continue to show up.
It's the timeline that we just saw on the screen
from our district leaders showing us the steps they need to
take to get this done right. So that's
what I'm listening to.
Anyone else?
There was two other questions that Mindy asked.
One was about
if boundary lines
aren't redrawn this year, won't this
bring current inequities forward?
I don't know if we have a great answer for that, but that's a good question to ask.
And then how to defend the more costly choice to not
reconfigure this year, given that we're so interested in reining
in the budget.
I do believe the math that-
reconfiguration is cost neutral, but I know that's something that we're going to
want more evidence on, and we're going to want to revisit with the committee.
Yeah, and I don't know. We
were presented with a budget
that was presented as budget neutral, as cost neutral to
reconfiguration versus redistricting for the year.
So there has been a lot of misinformation
that we might
actually,
that there's this sort of hidden extra cost we're
going to assume by not moving forward with
reconfiguration
in the 2026 fiscal year.
And,
Abigail, on the record, would you like to
clarify that again for the public,
how to accurately respond to that question?
Because I think if there
was a real financial-
Mm-hmm
... savings we were giving up, I think that's important for
the board to understand
before we decide on the timeline.
Yeah. So the budget,
the majority of costs are personnel.
So I build the budget based on lists of people, and the lists
of numbers of people that I received were the same.
So it did work out the same this year.
I think whether reconfiguration is cheaper or not,
I think we do need to explore it more with more financial
modeling.
I've done some various calculations with class sizes and
with one type of class size, I see distinct
drops in costs at certain thresholds, which is
really interesting, and then at other class sizes, I don't see the same effect.
I think it's really, really, really specific to
the specific people you have, the specific class sizes, and the
differences between schools in terms of number of classrooms that can
be accommodated. So I think it's a question that's worth
exploring more, but I think we have to do more exploration to provide
an even better answer.
Does that help?
Yeah. So we just don't know.
We don't have like a clear-
I think we have some valid assumptions.
Exactly. Right.
For sure.
Things like specialists serving specific grades, is that
more efficient with reconfiguration? Yes.
But I think there's a lot more to explore
to really know for sure, and it really depends on the specifics of our
situation, our schools, our capacity, and the different schools.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I have a couple things I wanted to say. I wanted to respond a little bit.
First of all, there are a bunch of different things here that are out there right
now.
I will say that
I want to address,
one, the superintendent search. Yeah.
We had some other
choices, and we didn't choose those.
And,
yeah.
I can see that. I can totally get that.
And,
yeah. Anyway,
I don't want to throw anybody under the bus.
And then,
about who comes to the meetings and doing outreach and so forth, that's
something that we could do a lot more work on.
And
that is a very long-- I think that when you think
of people who
feel empowered to show up and people who don't feel empowered to show up,
that goes down to specifics like whether you have a vehicle, and it goes
down to all kinds of other things, too. It isn't a simple formula.
We were supposed to have a meeting over in Red Bank, and we didn't end up doing
that. And it's not a question of flyers.
It's probably a question of a lot more stuff like that.
I was in a conversation with a PTA member about
some ideas around this kind of thing.
But it's undeniable.
It's not
just a question of having the doors open.
The kind of concerted effort that's needed, I
think it's something that merits thought, and
obviously whatever thought and action that was needed didn't happen before this
process. And I'm not holding anybody to that.
It's something that we need to look at systemically if we want to-- When I say
systemically, I mean within this environment of the school
board and the school system, how we would approach that.
And,
yeah. So again, one could go on about those things for a long time,
but it would be desirable, and
that's all. None of this looks great, I think.
And then was there something else? I think that's it for right now.
Thank you.
There's George.
Please.
I just wanted to assure Aiden that
I do have all of your questions.
I was going to do that as a question.
I'm the quickest stenographer up here, and I caught all of them.
But I also got your email today that had them.
So I'd just like maybe you to give me a call sometime, and
I think you've got good questions,
and I have some answers for you, for sure.
Thank you.
Marie.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Member Ritz.
Member Holmen had some good points, and what I think I see in front of
us is a superintendent
choosing-- We have an opportunity to establish a policy.
I think we had some new board members that didn't quite know what we were doing,
and if we establish a policy nowin the 20
years or later when we find another superintendent, we will have a policy
in place on what we could do. "This shall be true, this shall be true,
this shall be true." So I would invite us to take this as a learning
opportunity. I know it's too late.
We're having a meet and greet, which is nice, but to have a policy in
place for that, I think would be a good move forward.
Thank you.
There was another question that was about whether--
I'm not sure whether it was what the board felt or-- but
I think the question was, will the community have a chance to vote
publicly on the issue of reconfiguration?
I think-
That's right. Vlad asked that.
Yes. Okay.
Does anybody want to answer that?
I'll say my position.
My position is that
it's the board's decision, and this is a representative democracy,
and if you agree with our position, then you should run
against us.
We've really done our best to inform ourselves on
the issues, and talk to teachers, and talk to administrators, and go into the
schools, and really develop
an unbiased view of what reconfiguration will be.
And I think part of being a board member is you have different access to the
schools, I think, than most people.
And so I definitely feel better informed as a board member than I would
have as just a voter, as a community member.
And so I think for that reason, I think it is important for it to be the board's
decision.
Of course, taking input from everyone, and reading emails, and having phone
conversations, and talking to people.
That's how I feel.
And I did have this conversation with
Vlad, but I will say publicly, there is a process for public
referendum. So there's
two ways that it can happen. One is that the board makes a
recommendation to the city council.
It's ultimately the city council's decision whether they put a question out
for public referendum or not. And the
second way is through the
role of the public where--
and
what I said to Vlad is I didn't have all the details, but the city clerk
would have them, where you have to collect a certain
number of signatures, a certain percentage of the previous election,
and
to get that question on the ballot.
So I don't want to
give all the details of that because I don't know it, but there is a
process other than
the role of the board to make the decision
as Member Feller just spoke about, as representative government.
That's one way to proceed, and the other is that the
public always has the opportunity to
take action and bring something to public referendum.
So that's that question.
I just want to say I agree with Member Feller's
assessment that
I think it is fundamentally a
policy change which does fall within our purview, and
there is precedent. We're not going rogue here, contrary to maybe the
superintendent search.
There is precedent for
board making this kind of decision and-
This kind of decision, you mean?
Sorry. Making a decision on to reconfigure versus putting it to a
referendum.
Mm-hmm.
Member Risch.
And I just welcome the public's feedback.
In lieu of representation, I've been reading emails, and I really appreciate
people reaching out with constructive feedback. I've learned a lot.
Every month I come here, I learn. Every day I read my emails, I learn.
So keep the feedback coming.
Member Holman.
This is actually more of a question. So we have other things coming up.
Yeah.
Because we're going to be discussing more of the question of reconfiguration today,
right?
Correct.
This is not our time to necessarily to get into-
That's all right
... all our thoughts and things about that. But okay.
Thank you.
That's-- yeah.
Just other questions.
The superintendent spoke to Aiden, but I also made a copy of your
questions, so those questions will definitely be sent
forth to be asked.
Answered.
One of the other questions was,
how are the shifts for the DEI and the
director and the special ed director cost neutral?
And what I was referencing in that was that I
only know of a conversation that happened with one of those positions.
I don't know with the other. But where it was cost neutral in
terms of what the person was willing to
accept as a coordinator position and how that would
just result in being
not affecting the budget positively or negatively.
Can I just?
Please.
So I've heard that explanation
before. If in fact there's a
higher paid position that's eliminated and
a lower paid position is created, it indeed
is cost savings. And it's cost savings every
year that you have the lower paid
person doing whatever the other one was doing before.
So
there definitely is that. The other comment I'd like to say,
and this is probably the third time, been in a lot of districts.
I've worked in them, and I know a number of them, and I would
have to say that the group of leaders that we have
as directors is the smallest, and they
deal with, for me, what I see, the broadest
levels of need within a public school.
So I think right now
We are down to seven directors, and I would say
that that's as slim as an organization this size could
be.
For what it's worth.
Another question that came up was about the DEI director
and
how
eliminating that position
and/or not having a coordinator in
a leadership role
serves the needs of students
as we're trying to do reconfiguration.
I don't know if superintendent or anybody wants to address
that.
I think
that
Ximena Gilдо is
with us through the rest of this year. He should be involved.
And
we will have to look at what happens with the
coordinator position. It's not coordinator, I think it is-
Strategist
... strategist.
And that person should be immediately pulled into this as well.
And the other question was how to bring in families who are not yet in
the district. So I think that was coming from somebody who had
preschool-age children, and how
can we do a better job of bringing in those families into
communication?
So people who are outside of the district?
No, they're in the district, but they don't yet
have school-aged children.
Oh, okay.
Is that the meaning?
Good.
Babies all the way through.
Yeah.
How do we involve other members?
You've got two board members who don't have kids
in the district yet.
Yeah.
So I think there's some representation.
That's not really what the question was, Member Fowler.
The question was,
parents who are parents who have
preschool-aged kids, how can we do a better job?
I think this was the question.
That's okay.
How can we do a better job in communicating with them and bringing
them into the communication cycle?
So I think that's a question for you,
Superintendent.
I
think one of the things that we've done this year, the board has
authorized the district to become a community school
district.
Just that is a connection to a
community in a very different way than typical schools are.
So I think that
if I try to think of a better move than that, I
can't come up with one.
Can I-
Please
... add something?
Please.
Sorry that I'm not talking very much today. I feel pretty awful.
But I just want to say as the one person with
a kid not in school yet, I think one thing that
is going to be really important for us going forward, which we've already started
to do, is the work of connecting with day cares and as we
expand our pre-K and eventually three-year-old program,
find a way that all aspects of the community are connected
in that way from when a family enters into a day
care, for example, and moving forward.
And I think there's a lot of work we can do over the next year, and I appreciated
Member Richardson's point about
did we reach out to folks without
kids that are school-age yet. And I think over the next year, throughout this
reconfiguration planning process, trying to understand how we can better make those
connections and bring
families and day cares in particular in.
Thank you.
So we are now at the consent agenda, and if there were other questions that we
missed, and we will
get those. Some of them, like Aiden's questions, are written
down, which are really helpful, and so I appreciate you sending those in an email,
Aiden, and we'll get those answered as best we
can. Thank you.
With the consent agenda, the only item on the consent agenda is
the approval of the following personnel elections, Helen Pelletier
as interim principal
at Kaylor.
So if I can have a motion
to approve that, and a motion by
Richardson and seconded by Holman.
Member Richardson.
I specifically asked
our admin team if we felt that this role was
necessary
given there was a potential
delay to reconfiguration, and I'd like to read the response that I got because I
think it's important to be transparent about
all the
responsibilities that this role is going to
take on. And of course, I can't find it. Gosh darn it.
Because I have 1,000 emails from Johanna Prince.
Well, more like 600.
And I'm going to speak very
slowly.
I can't find it.
Do you want me to come up?
Yeah, would you just do it, please? I think it's important.
I want to give that air time. Thank you.
Sure. I think it's important to note that Helen Pelletier will allow Myra
Karen-
Myra
... to be on special assignment.
Right. Yeah.
So when I was writing, I was speaking about why we still needed a principal on
special assignment, and we're thrilled that Helen will be able to help us to allow
for that. The closure of Kaylor is complex.
Shutting down a building, preparing to move, getting
boxes,
thoseAnd honoring the community with the
celebration and closing out the family that they have
at Kahler is really important. In addition, the
principal on special assignment
has responsibilities for helping us prepare for the CDS
transition and ensuring that we are ready to
launch as
we take on that responsibility and bring on board our two new partners.
Plus, it is helping to set a really
strong foundation for the steering committee, such that that
work can continue into the year beyond.
And then it is also the work of preparing
for a more reduced
administration team and preparing for
curriculum council and thinking about what does grade
level leadership look like. So there's still a lot of work for us to
do that we absolutely feel that we need a
principal on special assignment for.
Can I ask a clarifying question?
Sure.
So is this role just to get us
through the summer? Or are we thinking that-
The principal on special assignment is now till
the end of school.
The contract that we have with Helen would take us a week after
school, just because there is sort of closure and shutdown
even in a standard year if Kahler were not closing its doors.
And then
we do not anticipate continuing the principal on special assignment
into next year. We'll have to think about that work.
I think the pace of work will change.
Right now we need to do a lot of that heavy foundational planning,
and then certainly the redistricting of the Kahler students, communicating with
families, hearing their needs, and just making sure that folks feel like
they know what to expect in their transition.
Thanks. And did you talk about how it was funded? Did you say that?
Sure. So the funding to allow for this
is we have early seed money from our CDS
funding source that we are allowed to access prior
to the July 1 fiscal date. So that's how
we will support the next eight
weeks or so.
Thank you.
Thank you. You all set?
Yep.
Anybody else?
All those in favor of 5.1, which is the approval of the
following elections, Helen Pelletier as interim principal at
Kahler.
And opposed? And that is unanimous. Thank you.
We have multiple
items
before us, so I'm going to suggest that we take four at a
time and have one motion to approve four.
So one, two, three, four. One, two, three.
One, two, three, four. One, two, three.
I've got them.
Yeah. Okay.
So starting with consideration and action to identify
a final percentage of impact.
Well, this one might be separate.
No, I was-- Yeah, this-
Yeah, this one.
Really.
Okay, I got you. I got you. Yeah.
We'll do this one, and then we'll split them.
I got you. Okay, thank you. So the first one we will do alone.
Consideration and action to identify a final percentage
of impact on taxes between 6%,
which is current, not to exceed 7% maximum advised by the city
council to be held in contingency accounts specify
the percentage increase. So we need
somebody to move this motion with a percentage increase, and
then a second, and then we can discuss it.
Member Smith.
I would propose 7%.
Okay. So,
Member Smith proposes 7%. Is there a second?
And the second is
Member Teller.
So, Member Smith.
Yeah, I just think it's crucial that we take every opportunity we can
to
add to our contingency accounts. And I think
it's going to be up to us to sell to the public that this makes sense
and that we're making financially responsible moves going forward.
And I think it's worth taking that shot.
Member Teller.
Yep. I agree with Member Smith.
I think we're in a real fix here
financially. I think this has been a budget
that has incurred and will continue to incur a ton of
pain
across the district, both for staff and students.
I think,
even with that pain,
we need to raise some funds for contingency to prevent
more pain in the future. So I think worst case scenario for us is
not having contingency account. There's some kind of unforeseen facility
issue, and to
be able to provide a building for our students to go to school in, we have to
eliminate staff, right? That is absolutely the worst case scenario, and
I think by raising additional funds to go in contingency and then into
reserve the following year, I think we can protect that risk.
So, I'm for this.
Before we go to further discussion, I'm going to ask the superintendent
to give us his recommendation and view of this
item.
Superintendent Entwistle.
I
would just suggest to the board that they consider
the highly unusual action of a city
supporting
a
school board, like has just happened, up to
$2 million.
And I feel that we were getting signals from the board.
I mean, sorry-
Council, you mean? From the council.
From the council.
Okay. Yeah.
Sorry.
Signals from the council
that in fact they felt with the
bailout, essentially,
that they were hoping that, not hoping, they
suggested that we stay at 6%.
I would agree with that, just because
it is so unusual to be in a situation like this
and have that situation get completely remediated so
that you are really at least
on floor level,
not below, and you've got a place to build from.
But of course, the board will make that
decision.
Member Holman.
I attended the meeting last night at the city council, and
basically, I concur with what our superintendent just
said,
that
it probably makes sense for us to keep it as low as we can.
And I do want to be able to add to our contingency, but
being able to head in without debt is a big help.
And
at least one council member
told us that he had
been receiving
concern
emails from the community about how much taxes were going to be.
And that's one of the things that could
sink our budget, although there is normally a pretty low turnout, keeping in mind
there's a primary. So this will be much higher than the average
year.
So there will be more people there.
Anyway, so that's my kind of thought, and I
wish
we could just have as much money as we want, but...
Member Richardson.
I'm not sure we had support to go to 7% last night.
We didn't. No.
We didn't.
Yeah. So I think
it's tricky to...
I'm sorry, I'm looking at my notes from last night's meeting.
Yeah. Claire, Member Holman-
Okay
... Chair DeAngelis, and myself were there last night, and
I've been a pretty vocal proponent of going over
6%,
just because
it felt
irresponsible to not have a fund balance.
But what council
did, did change the dynamics of
our
debt. We aren't going to be
shouldered with debt in a way that
we thought we were,
and
we continue to receive a lot-- This is a very
unpopular budget.
I'd like to not give anybody any more reasons to not
support this budget.
I don't want to be back here in June, having to cut more staff because we
were risky and-- I would love to have a
contingency
or a fund balance. My hope is that Abigail
has over-budgeted conservatively, liberally,
whichever way that gets us some money in the bank at the end of the-
Or that she prints money down in the basement.
Yeah, or that, too. I'm still looking for that million dollars in my backyard.
So
I'm feeling a
little
grateful for what we got, and I did
say publicly last night that I wouldn't support anything beyond 6%, and also I
don't think we have the-
Yeah, so we can't even-
So I don't think we can. I was saying to myself today, could we do
6.25 and bring back the percussion ed
tech, because I am terrified of our band
and-
It is very sad
... the band department. The band leader leading a room of
70 plus children with instruments, that sounds crazy to me.
And we have received a tremendous amount of support
for that role, and it feels like we are cutting a
pretty significant curriculum. So that was, in my mind, where I was
thinking, if 6.25 felt like
something maybe we could get behind.
But I'm
not going to be the lone voice on that.
Member Rizz.
I support the 6%.
I was originally for contingency plan, but it was kind of
a blessing that they gave us the grant that they're talking about, and I
really appreciate it. And if we stay to the plan 6%, I think we're
honoring some more promises we had made to a budget that was constrained
to 6%. So to change that now would be
complicated. So 6% it is for me.
Member Fowler.
So,
it seems like the language of this agenda item may be a little bit
outdated given what happened last night.
Yeah.
Other board members, could we get to a place where we go to
6.25%?
Anybody
willing to support that?
I'm confused. Are we allowed to vote on this?
Yes, we are allowed to vote on it. So let me clarify.
Member Richardson is correct. The
guidance we got last night was to 6%.
If we go higher, and we could go higher-
Still have to approve it.
Well, the council then has the ability to
say they're going to. All they do is say they're going to either move the budget
forward or they're not.
I can assure you, they're
not going to not move the budget forward.But they were
expressing caution last night, which is what we heard-
Mm-hmm
... and clear guidance that their preference would be that we
stay at 6%.
Yeah.
And
yeah, that was their
preference and their guidance.
In
a-
Member Feller.
I would expect that they're quite well tuned in
to what voters outside of the orbit of the school district are
feeling. I heard on one of those calls
Member Matthews saying, "For as many people I get in support of the school
budget, there's people saying, 'My taxes are too high, I'm going to vote down the
school budget.'" So if they're giving that 6% guidance, then
I think they probably understand the public sentiment pretty
well.
Can we-- I'm sorry. Dr. Prince has some notes from last
night that I'd love to have her
clear, if that's okay.
Yes, absolutely.
Last night there were six members in attendance.
Four of them said they would be a no vote to move the budget forward
above 6%, is the notes that I took. So
again, they were not taking a vote last night,
and perhaps if you make a compelling case, but I wrote
down they said, "Get out your pencils," and
I wrote down exactly what they said.
And four of them-
They won't come back
... four of them said it will be a no vote if it's above 6%.
So does that agree with what you heard last night?
Doesn't agree with what I heard, but that's okay. That's all right.
I don't think we should go above 6% myself, but-
I think that's what they said last night
... Member Smith.
Yeah. I'll just apologize for not being there last night, and I would like
to rescind the motion. I think that sends a pretty clear message from the
city, whether it's-
Do you want to just accept a friendly amendment to drop that 7 to 6?
Sure. Drop it to six.
Okay. So,
if we have the consideration and action, and is that
okay with the seconder?
Yeah, that's fine.
Yeah.
Okay. So consideration and action to identify a final
percentage of impact on taxes
at six, not to exceed,
specify not to exceed 6%.
To be held in contingency blah, blah, blah. Okay.
A specific number.
Yes, that's what I'm saying, 6%.
About 6%.
So consideration and action to identify a final
percentage
of
6%.
Yeah.
Okay.
To be held in contingency.
Yeah, we're taking all that out.
Okay.
Yeah.
Because they know-
So that the motion-
It's going to sit with seven
... would say, "Consideration and action to identify a final
percentage of impact on taxes of
6%."
That's all we would say.
Yeah. All I think you would say.
Does that make sense to everybody? Is that okay? Okay.
All those in favor?
Oh.
All those-
Sorry.
And oppose? Okay, so that's unanimous.
Wait, what?
Yeah, it was unanimous. Yeah, I've already voted.
I'm sorry, Daniel, I didn't see. Did you have your hand up?
I did.
Okay. Thank you.
All right, so the next four are consideration and action to
adopt personnel reductions.
That's a separate one, too.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Yes.
Okay. The next one is a separate one.
Consideration and action to adopt personnel reductions as presented
and consistent with the final 2026-'27
school board budget. So I need a motion
to pass to put that on the table.
Moved by Member Rish and seconded by Member
Holman.
Okay.
Okay. Member Rish.
I think we should just approve this.
There's been a lot of planning, and it's time to make it final.
That's all I have.
Member Holman.
Nothing to say.
Other comments?
Anybody have...
Member Feller.
Yeah. I
think I speak for everyone on the board when I say how
sorry
we are for all the impacted staff.
It's
really unfortunate, and I think
this board can do more to make sure that we're never in this
position again.
It's
really hard
to do this. There's so many dedicated staff in South Portland.
Parents,
community members just speak so highly of all the staff, regardless of whether
you're an ed tech or a teacher or support staff or a custodian or bus driver,
and I'm so sorry that we're in this spot.
Member Smith.
Yeah, I agree with everything Daniel said, and I just
want to make it clear that I think this budget,
and the work that the admin has done, I know there are disagreements out there
about particular positions, and that it's really hard to make
decisions in any specific direction.
The goal of passing this budget is so that when we hire
someone to the South Portland School District, that we can keep them,
and that we can give them a job that they know that is secure.
And it's really hard
for us to do that right now. And next year, there's going to be a lot of
question marks.
And so I'm going to do everything that I can, and I know the board is, over the
next 12 months, to make sure that the administration is doing everything that they
can to make sure that
the positions that we have will be able to stay, and that we can
ensure that there's some stability in our school district, because that is really
the most paramount
objective for all of us right now. So
that's all I got.
Member Richardson?
Yeah, I
don't know. I
really wish that we could've
willed out a few more positions.
I'm concerned about what our schools look like next year.
I think, however, I'm not
concerned by the people leaving the students, and
I
don't know if there's some kind of
vibe check we can have on sizes of classrooms,
like whether
enrollment in band is still skyrocketing or decreasing.
I'd like some kind of inflection point
that the reductions that were made aren't actually
causing damage, which I don't know how
to do that thoughtfully, but
I do understand that we were
heavily staffed. I do. That is clear based
on the comparisons that we've seen across other districts.
But I would like us to consider how we are checking in to
make sure that
these reductions are actually not
causing harm.
Thank you. Other comments?
I guess I would say that
there's no one that it wasn't valuable, and it's really
just awful to be in this position, and
yeah, I'm hoping that we can
continue to foster wellbeing within this department, within this district
as much as possible, financial and
of all the people who work here.
Member Feller.
Yeah, just quickly.
I think I'm going to trust our administration
when they say that our special education rooms are staffed
appropriately, but I really think as we move into next school
year, we need to be on high alert for staffing issues in special
education. And,
given these CVS regulations, if it seems
like there are real safety concerns, there's really high
staff turnover right at the beginning of the year because the rooms aren't staffed
appropriately, we have to hire more people. Right?
So let's be very reactive to that.
That's all I'll ask.
Response. I'm going to offer an amendment
that might not get a second, but I'm going to offer the
amendment that we
move the position of strategist for the DEI to
a DEI coordinator in a way that is revenue
neutral so that there is no change in the budget,
but that it creates the position from strategist to
coordinator rather than...
And
yeah. Anyway,
I'm going to make that amendment, and if there's a second, we can discuss it.
If there isn't, then
that's fine.
Okay. That fails for lack of a second.
We're on to just voting on consideration and action to
adopt personnel reductions as presented and consistent with the
final 26/27 school board
budget.
All those in favor?
And opposed? That's unanimous.
Now are we up to four?
Yeah. We're coming up to them now. Right now.
6.3, 6.4, 6.5-
And 6.6
... 6.6.
Okay. Consideration and action to authorize that
$28,019,115
be expended for regular instruction.
6.4, consideration and action to authorize
$16,121,654
be expended for special education.
Consideration and action to authorize that
$0 be expended for career and technical
education, and consideration and action to
authorize that
$1,286,516
be expended for other instruction.
So we can take one motion moved by Member Feller
and seconded by Member Holman.
Member Feller.
Yeah. Just again, on the special education piece,
I know that we have some momentum to start the budget discussions
quite a bit earlier next year in October, and I really want to take a
hard look at special education,
and just make sure we're staffed appropriately there.
Thank you. Member Holman.
I just want to make sure that everybody understands that that zero for career and
technical education doesn't mean that it's not offered.
It just means that it's not a funding stream that we have to be concerned about.
That it's otherwise taken care of.
Thank you.
All those in favor of 6.3, 6.4, 6.5, and
6.6?
And opposed? And that is unanimous.
So then we have 6.7, 6.8, 6.9, and
6.10. Consideration and action to authorize
that $4,936,016 be
expended for student and staff support.
6.8, consideration and action to authorize that
$2,897,113
be expended for system administration.
6.9, consideration and action to authorize that
$3,177,865
be expended for school administration.
And 6.10, consideration and action to authorize that
$3,288,253
be expended for transportation and buses.Do I have
a motion to approve those four? Moved by Member Smith
and seconded by Member Richardson, who's putting up her
hand. Thank you.
By Member Richardson. Okay, Member Smith.
I got nothing.
You're all set. Okay. Anything? Okay.
All those in favor of 6.7, 6.8, 6.9, and
6.10.
And that is also unanimous.
And then we have 6.11, consideration and-
I just suggest we'll get to the bottom of this page, so just 11,
12, and 13.
Okay. That's what I was going to do.
Oh, good.
6.11 is consideration and action to authorize that
$7,461,844
be expended for facilities maintenance.
6.12, consideration and action to authorize
that
$8,099,300...
and I'm hoping I'm reading these numbers right, $359
be expended for debt service and other
commitments. And 6.13, consideration and
action to authorize that
$635,867 be
expended for all other expenditures.
Do I have a motion to approve?
Member Risch,
and seconded by Member
Feller.
Member Risch, any comment?
I have no additional comments.
Okay. And Member Feller?
No additional comments.
All right. All those in favor of 6.11, 6.12, and
6.13. And that's unanimous.
Okay. Now we're on 6.14, consideration and
action to authorize that
$48,510,979 be
appropriated
for the total cost of funding public education from
pre-kindergarten to grade 12, as described in the Essential Programs
and Services Funding Act,
and that
$37,287,295
be raised as the city's contribution to the total cost
of funding public education from pre-kindergarten to grade
12, as described in the Essential Programs and
Services Funding Act, in accordance with the Maine Revised
Statutes Title 20A, Section
15688. And there's an explanation that I
don't need to read.
You might want to take the next one as well.
Oh, okay. 6.15, consideration and action
to authorize that
$3,737,171
be raised and appropriated for the annual payments on debt
service
previously approved by the voters for non-state funded
school construction projects and non-state funded
portions of school construction projects,
in addition to the funds appropriated as the local
share of the city's contribution to the total cost of
funding public education from pre-kindergarten to grade 12.
So, 6.14 and 6.15. Do I
have a motion to approve? Moved by Member
Feller and seconded by Member Holman.
Any
comment on this, Member Feller?
No.
And Member Holman?
Okay. Anybody else? All those in favor?
And that's unanimous.
Great. Thank you. 6.16, consideration and
action to authorize that
$18,268,100 be raised and
appropriated in additional local funds which
exceed the state's Essential Programs and Services allocation
model by
$18,268,100,
as required to fund the budget recommended by the Board of Education.
The Board of Education recommends
$18,268,100 for additional
local funds and gives the following reasons for
exceeding the state's Essential Programs and Services funding
model by
$18,268,100. Additional
education costs not recognized by EPS,
staffing for nursing, guidance, and library services
greater than acknowledged by EPS, class size targets lower
than the state standard, and additional debt service for the new
athletic grass field. So, that's
6.16.
And 6.17 is consideration and action to
authorize that the Board of Education
be authorized to expend
$75,923,601
for the fiscal year beginning July 1, 2026,
and ending June 30th, 2027, from the
municipality's contribution to the total cost of funding
public education from pre-kindergarten to grade
12,
as described in the Essential Programs and Services Funding Act,
non-state funded school construction projects, additional
local funds for school purposes under Maine Revised
Statutes Title 20A, Section 15690,
unexpended balances, tuition receipts,
state subsidy, and other receipts for the support of schools.
So, 6.16 and 6.17. Do I have a
motion to approve? Moved by Feller
and seconded by Richardson.
Any comments?
No comments.
Seeing none, all those in favor?And
that's unanimous.
So I'm going to do the last--
Can I do the last? No. I'm going to do the last three.
You could do the last three.
Okay.
So 6.18, consideration and
action to authorize the City of South Portland to appropriate
$250,000 for adult education and
raise $250,000 as the local share
with authorization to expend any additional incidental or
miscellaneous receipts in the interest and for the well-being of the
adult education program. 6.19, consideration
and action to authorize the Board of Education to expend
such other sums as may be received from state and federal
grants or programs or other sources during the fiscal year
for school and/or adult education purposes, provided
that such grants, programs, or other sources do not require the
expenditure of other funds not previously
appropriated. And 6.20, consideration and
action to authorize the Board of Education to use all or
part of additional state subsidy received, if any, to increase
expenditures for school purposes in cost center
categories approved by the school board, increase the allocation of
finances in a reserve fund approved by the school board
and/or decrease the local cost share
expectation as defined in Title 20A, Section
15671-A1B
for local property taxpayers for funding public education as
approved by the school board. So if I can have a motion to approve
6.18, 6.19, and 6.20. Moved by
Member Holman. Okay.
And seconded by Member Smith.
And any discussion?
Seeing none, all those in favor?
And that's also unanimous.
And that brings us up to consideration and action for the board
to adopt the resolution to amend a prior board
action regarding pre-K to 4
grade configuration timeline and implementation guidance.
And
this resolution reads, "Whereas on March
30th, 2026, the South Portland School Board
voted to close James O. Caylor Elementary School
at the conclusion of the 25-26 school year,
and to reconfigure the four remaining elementary schools,
Helen H. Dyer, Dora L. Small, Frank I.
Brown, and Dr. Waldo T. Skillen, by grade
bands, with Dyer and Small serving
pre-kindergarten through grade one, and Brown and Skillen
serving grades two through four. And whereas the board
recognizes the importance of ensuring that any
grade reconfiguration is implemented thoughtfully
with a primary focus on the academic, social, and emotional needs of
students. And whereas the board seeks to provide
additional time to support effective planning,
communication, and implementation of the elementary school
configuration model.
Now, therefore, be it resolved that the board hereby amends
its prior action
to require that the elementary grade reconfiguration be implemented
no later than the start of the
2027-2028 school year in place of the
previously established timeline.
And be it further resolved that the board directs the superintendent and
school administration to develop a reconfiguration
implementation plan
in a manner that prioritizes the academic needs of students
and is guided by the following policy objectives.
One, minimizing disruption to students, including
maintaining continuity of peer groups and learning
environments where feasible. Two, minimizing
student transportation times to the greatest extent practicable.
Three,
maximizing the efficient use of building
capacity across the school department.
Four,
ensuring consistency in instructional methods, curriculum,
and learning materials across grade levels and schools.
Five, preserving, and where possible,
enhancing access to core academic programs and
student support services, including special education
services,
homeless intervention services, and multilingual learner services.
Six,
minimizing increases to class sizes consistent
with available resources and sound
educational practice. Seven,
providing robust transition supports for students,
including social, emotional, and academic supports,
as well as opportunities for orientation and school community
building. Eight, ensuring proactive and
transparent communication and outreach to parents, guardians,
and school department staff, including clear articulation of the
educational rationale for the contemplated
reconfiguration. Nine, ensuring compliance
with all applicable laws and collective bargaining agreements,
including fulfillment
of any required meet and consult obligations and continuity of
services required under student support plans.
10, preserving instructional time for students.
11, supporting staff transitions with any
necessary team adjustments, including
minimizing involuntary displacement where practicable.
And 12-Promoting equitable outcomes for all students,
including careful consideration of the impacts on
historically underserved student population.
Be it further resolved that all board decisions required for
the 2027 implementation, including attendance
boundaries, student assignment decisions, bell times,
and transportation framework shall be brought forward and voted upon no
later than the regular board meeting in November 2026.
The motion is consideration and action for the board to
adopt the resolution to amend a prior board
action regarding
pre-K to four grade configuration timeline and
implementation
guidance.
So I need someone to move the motion with a second and we
can discuss.
Member Smith.
Moved by Member Smith
and seconded by Member Risch.
Member Smith.
I'm going to vote for this resolution, but it feels really
hard.
I've been pretty clear that I'm a very
active proponent for reconfiguration.
I think the logic
was very obvious to me that in a budget where we're cutting $8.5
million and 12% of our staff and closing the
elementary school, that
when we already have elementary schools that are highly
inequitable in terms of resource distribution, that we're only going to exacerbate
that problem by maintaining K four schools into next year, and that we're going to
make it really hard,
particularly for Kahler families.
And,
I totally understand and appreciate the anger that
Kahler families have over this decision, and that they were
asked to get on board with reconfiguration and to consider it.
And then here we are
rejecting that. And I think
it's really tough.
The thing I think that pushed me in this direction primarily
was
seeing the lack of trust and support,
particularly from our teachers, in making this happen.
It was my belief that when we voted on this, that,
yes, this implementation was going to be rocky and it was going to be fast, but
ultimately, it was going to get us to a better position than a situation
where our K four schools have higher class
sizes and fewer resources, and they're already inequitably distributed.
And so,
that was the rationale for my vote, but recognizing that there was
just not a lot of trust that a plan was going to be put together that made sense,
and that was going to be fair, and that was going to accurately represent
the costs. And,
I didn't want to be someone who stood in the way of what I saw
as a real lack of trust from teachers.
And in the same way that I voted for this budget in saying that
I want to build a district that our teachers can
want to work at, and our teachers believe that they will have a job next
year. I also want them to believe that
the district is keeping them
informed and also engaged in the process of
making decisions. And so that was really
what tipped it for me. And so I'm going to support this motion.
But I think it comes with very real costs, and I think next year is going
to be hard, particularly for students who have the most needs and need our
schools the most.
And that this is going to be 12 months where,
if we had reconfigured, it would've looked better for a lot of folks.
So that's all I want to say for now. But...
Member Risch. Thank you.
I'm going to vote for this resolution, and it's part of my learning what it is to
be a school board member. I made the original determination
assuming certain things would come together in a certain timeline, but this will
give us another timeline to work around.
And this is not voting against reconfiguration.
It's voting for something that could be more sincere and
involved with the community.
And, I think we need to do some listening.
And,
I hope to learn more by November. So, thank
you.
Mm-hmm.
I have some questions and some comments.
So one of my questions is, looking down at the it be further
resolved section
of this motion,
that all board decisions required for the
2027 implementation, including attendance,
blah,
blah, blah, shall be brought forward and voted upon.
So
that
means that all the decisions of the...
I'm concerned. I
feel like we had the information about reconfiguring really at the end of
our previous study on boundaries and
configurations, and I've said that before.
And, I was like, "Let's just do it right now,"
then, and that didn't happen. And
I'm concerned that this will
be a chance, like what Mindy Allo said.
I'm very concerned that this is a path that leads us to not
doing this. Someone who's not here tonight,
but she's been to several of these meetings, was saying we've been talking about
this for 20 years. I just feel like,
I think there's a real opportunity for us, and I understand
completely that there are
reasons why.
I understand the other side of it, I really do, that
in some ways, it's really nice to have
your whole family in the same school and have the bigger kids around,
too. I do see that. Having the bigger kids around does make sense in a lot of ways.
But-But I think that one big difference from,
say, when I went to school and we had kindergarten through
sixth grade in one school, which was, of course, in ancient times,
but
is that the density of services is
incomparable. We are
required, we choose to, and we are also, to a large extent,
required to offer a density of services that is just not comparable
to how it has been. And
will we get more kids? Are we eventually going to
have a larger population? We did have a surge. That was amazing.
That enabled us to fold in a whole school's worth of young
people across the grades when that happened.
But is that ever going to happen again?
Are we going to
be able to refill these schools? It'd be great to think that we could, but
that's not the trend.
One could go on about that. It's not the trend in a lot
of parts of the world,
the developed world. And
so
if we're going to continue to offer that density of services,
we want to have a place where
our employees can work, be well-paid, and consider that they're going to have
a job for a while, then we have to begin to think about maybe we can't
spread the services out that far. And so that's one, I do think over
time, reconfiguration is going to be more sensible for us.
And
I don't love everything about it, but I do think it probably is the way for us to
go. And I'm really concerned that if we don't rip the Band-Aid off, what's going to
happen? And
so, I
want to hear more. I want to hear more of this discussion right now because I do
have some really deep concerns about it.
At the same time, I've understood the concerns from
educators who have said that they need more time.
I've heard those concerns, and I don't think those are
unrealistic. They probably are.
Do I think that we couldn't possibly do it?
I think we could do it right away if we needed to.
I feel truly conflicted about it. I'm not sure, because I'm so
worried that it's going to be a kick the can, and I don't want to see that.
At the same time,
I don't want to be
the board that we're just a bunch of jerks and didn't listen to anybody.
But you may end up that way anyhow, because they're going to be a group of people
that they don't want it to happen because they just don't want it to happen, and
this is supposed to be a reason for it not to happen.
So
this is a very hard decision. And
honestly, I'm really teetering. I'm
standing on a thing like this, teetering around thinking about what to do
because I do feel that reconfiguration is probably the right way for us to go, is
the right way for us to go, and that I'm concerned to open
up the path for it not to happen. And yet I do want
to proceed sanely and with community input,
and having extended timeline would offer that.
So,
that's really my thinking. I'm up to the last minute
here, friends.
Member Fowler.
Thank you, Member Holman.
Yeah. I have some thoughts to share on reconfiguration and also the
timeline. So I feel like I have a pretty balanced perspective.
I can see small school from my house.
When I talk to my neighbors, they do not want reconfiguration.
They want to walk their kids for four years.
But on the other hand, I've talked to a lot of teachers in the schools and
heard they haven't been unanimous in support of reconfiguration, but I would
say the majority of them think it's what our schools need.
And actually, one of my favorite things, I studied
philosophy in college and my favorite paper of all time was by Martha
Nussbaum, and it was about being an insider and outsider at the same time.
So you can have two perspectives, and that really is a privilege to have those two
perspectives. So I want to talk right now to the people who
really don't want reconfiguration to happen, and I want to try
to outline the rationale for reconfiguration.
So the first one is differentiated instruction.
So differentiated instruction
is new to me this year. It's a pretty well-known kind of framework for
teaching, and it's about having mixed-ability
classrooms. And when you hear people talk about Tier 1 instruction, it's like
what you think about when you think about an elementary school classroom.
There's kids at different reading levels, kids at different math levels.
And inside a mixed-ability classroom, because what you don't want to do is
segregate kids in the classrooms based on abilities,
is you want the teacher to be able to teach to each student
wherever they are.
And so that might mean
helping some students understand the concepts that they need to do the math
lesson while other kids are just ripping through their math worksheet.
So being able to teach to both ability levels.
It's self-evident that's very hard.
There's a lot of planning time that is necessary to teach to mixed-ability
classrooms. When you have three second-grade
classrooms in a school rather than six, it's harder to do that.
So I really do understand this argument for
collaboration between teachers.
So
making differentiated instruction easier to perform is
the first rationale for reconfiguration.
The second rationale for reconfiguration is it drives efficiencies.
So right now, I think many people know this, specialists are traveling
from one building to another,
and they're working with students in relatively small groups at one school.
So because those groups are small and because those specialists are traveling,
that means they can spend less time with students who need the support.
So by consolidating these grade bands into schools and
saying, "This specialist is going to stay at this school all day," that
means more students get access to those specialists.
So for me, that is a no-brainer in favor of
reconfiguration.And finally, this idea of distributing
need. So, I was blown away to learn this week
that there's 108 students at Skillen who need English
language instruction, and there's 10 students at Small who need
English language instruction. That is a big gap.
And
I'm not under the illusion that reconfiguration is going to
completely balance the needs in our district, but I think it can make
it better. That being said, I do have
concerns about reconfiguration.
Transitions aren't good for students. This is pretty well documented.
There's a lot of research. There's one incredible study out of MIT that showed this
in the New York City school system. It was a really good study.
So transitions aren't good for students.
The benefits of reconfiguration must outweigh the
adverse impacts of transitions on students. So that's very important.
The costs. We've heard that reconfiguration is budget neutral.
Ideally it would save dollars,
but I think for the committee to
really make the argument that it's doing the most with the
dollars that we have, I think is going to be a very important thing to bring the
community along.
What are the impacts on families? That's another concern I have.
How about families that have kids in three schools?
We need to make sure that working families
can benefit
from this reconfiguration. And finally, impact on the city.
I think, are we going to have buses on
the streets all day? So,
I see reconfiguration happening in 2027 as the
compromise that our city needs to move
forward. It's truly a compromise.
Mm-hmm.
And I think it can bring everybody together.
I think we can all work together. Clearly, a very activated,
intelligent community here, and I
think this next 17 months is going to be a really good
one. It's going to be really collaborative, and I think we'll see
really good things from everybody in South Portland.
So I'm going to vote for this.
But that being said, I do have these concerns, and I want to stay on top of them,
and I want to make sure that it's a really well thought out, well
executed plan.
My turn.
Member Risch was-
Oh, you
can go. I don't really want to go.
The only thing I'd say is
we really need to get going on this.
November 26th is when we have to have some plans together.
We don't have that long. So let's get it done.
It started yesterday, and I appreciate the listening.
That's the first part of it.
But it's a short time. We're not really given much time.
And just to add, this is a political body.
Whatever happens in the next election happens, and whoever is
representative here. But I still believe in
reconfiguration based on my conversations with some teachers.
And it pains me that we're not doing it this year, but this is the best compromise,
I think.
Member Richardson.
Ideally, we
would've talked about closing a school two years ago.
Ideally, we were looking at enrollment projections and
we're able to have a timeline that looked like
this, that talked about closure of a school and reconfiguration all at the same
time. That's the ideal. And that's the only
reason I didn't vote for reconfiguration initially was
because I was really concerned about the amount
of our capacity to absorb
a 12% staff cut, a closure of a school,
and a reconfiguration.
This resolution
checks the box
on giving us more time from a capacity perspective.
Is it fair that we have to do it the way that we're doing it?
No, it's not fair.
But I really would've
loved to hear more of an opinion from our district team,
because in my conversations with them personally,
they have welcomed the benefit of time.
And they are the doers of this plan, and I think
an actual opinion from them would've been helpful.
Then it's not just the six of us kind of dictating when
things can happen. I think it's very uncomfortable to see a timeline like this
and say, "No, you must do this in three months."
Because we're not the doers of that,
of the plan. I
think it's important that we do this vote in November to
assure the--
To sort of
address the concerns that a new
board could come in. There are, I think,
three seats
with terms that are open, or that I think will be open. One of them is mine.
And I
feel confident that this board is
on board with reconfiguration.
If those three seats change, you still have a
majority of a board that's committed to the plan.
So I've said this many times, I think it's
really unlikely that there's going to be some kind of switch.
What I did say to a parent today was that if reconfiguration
proves to cost us millions and millions of dollars, then that seems
financially irresponsible.
But
that seems likely impossible, right?
So,
barring that, and
II think all of us would have to think long and
hard about a policy change that's very expensive, but that does not appear to
be the case with this plan. And I do think it's going to be crucial to
show enrollment projections against projected
savings so that we can really sell this better to the community so that the
buy-in is easier and that
the--
I don't know.
This looks like a different time. Is this a different timeline? No.
But the visits, I don't know. There's a lot of positive stuff happening after the
board approves this in the beginning of 2027,
and
that's exciting. I also want to say that
when this conversation started with boundaries and configuration, and then it kind
of petered out,
and perhaps it's the
financial
instability that we're feeling, but it does feel like this community is
way more open to the change
in a way that what I witnessed
a couple of years ago, they were not.
And so I don't want to hold history against our community.
Many people in this room showed up initially
anti-reconfiguration, and you showed up
weeks and weeks and weeks, and you
are now a proponent of it. So
that's positive, and we can build on that.
And yeah, I think staying optimistic and positive and
not going down rabbit holes of what-ifs isn't going to
do anybody any good. I think we all have a goal. We're working towards it.
That's what this timeline shows, and there shouldn't be any reason that
we're not moving forward with the goal.
So thank you.
I tried to write down my comments in an effort to be focused.
So first I want to say, when I speak from this dais as
chair, I speak for the board, but when I speak on a topic
that's being debated, I speak for myself.
And my personal vote may not match the will of this body,
but I will always, as I'm expected to do for as long as I'm a board
member, support the majority vote of this board.
So I've answered more than 300 emails.
I apologize if I missed yours. I've tried to be responsive to
everyone. I've spoken on the phone to more than four dozen people, and
I've personally met with at least two dozen people one-on-one,
and
about three dozen in groups. And I've spoken with people who are not at
these meetings.
I appreciate all the feedback, and I truly feel it's important.
While we may not always agree, I've tried my best to listen and
respond,
and I'm not perfect.
I'm doing my best as a volunteer, as a lifelong educator, and a person
who cares deeply about this community and the people in it.
And I've learned a great deal about why some folks want more time, including things
I had not considered.
Many are experiencing still the results of COVID, many
are hearing this for the first time and feel blindsided, and many have
questions that are still unanswered, and these questions are valid and
important.
And I've asked for answers to some of these questions multiple times, as has the
public.
But Mindy Alo said something tonight that really
stuck with me, and I wrote it down. She said, "Perfect, no,
but progress, yes."
And
I've also heard from those who think the time is now for a lot of
reasons, and she's one of them. My concerns include
that several surveys used allowed for folks to reply more than
once, that one survey went out to all levels of staff,
and many feel this was not reasonable as the decision doesn't affect all
staff.
Members of the former Boundaries and Configurations Committee
report that concerns given are things that have been stated
before and who believe those issues will not change.
The Kaylor families and staff feel abandoned and
believe that the time of school closure should go hand-in-hand with
reconfiguration, meaning it should happen now.
I've been called out for what I've said, for what I believe, for how I
vote.
I've received emails and finally phone calls that resulted in a report to
the police when I did not feel safe.
Yeah, that was me.
I've been told that the effort to recall my election, which is
based on how I voted, would go away if I did what was asked
of me,
but I don't make my decisions that way.
I've even offered to meet with the person who took out the recall papers, but
there's been no willingness to do that.
First, this board cannot require an action of a future board.
We can specify a preference. We can pass a
policy. We can provide goals moving forward, but we
cannot require anything to happen.
And second, this document before us does not outline the specifics of
reconfiguration as we agreed in our
five-to-two vote. It was not
a divided vote. It was a five-to-two vote.
That decision clearly outlined
that two schools would be pre-K to one,
and two would be two to four. This action does not include that.
And third, I will not vote because of a threat or a promise.
I will always remain true to my convictions and will always vote in a
way that remains loyal to my beliefs.
I think the night we voted to close Kaylor School, we also made a
promise. Our vote of five to two said we will do
reconfiguration, and we will do it now.To renege on that
promise is not something I can do.
I continue to believe reconfiguration is best for all kids,
that it is the beginning of our equity work, not the end,
and that the district administration is capable of making that happen.
I do believe there are questions that should be answered in the short run, and I
believe we can do that.
I continue to believe that the time is now, and that to delay
is to increase the chance that this district will not move forward.
While I will likely be the minority tonight,
I will first vote for what I think is right.
After that, and as I said, for as long as I'm a board member,
I will do what is expected of me. I will support the majority vote.
I will not work behind the scenes to sabotage any decision this
board makes, but rather, I will be committed to the voice of the majority
as democracy demands. Thank you.
Are there any other comments?
Seeing none, all those in favor of the motion.
I have Risch,
Richardson,
Feller,
Smith,
and Holman.
And opposed is DeAngelis.
And the motion passes with Risch, Richardson, Feller, Smith,
and Holman voting for it, and one opposition was
DeAngelis.
So that action passes.
We are back to the second public comment.
And are there people who are wanting to speak?
Because I will just need to read the public comment again.
I've
got one.
Okay. As this is public proceeding, unless... Whoops, I'm sorry.
That's not it.
Public comment is an opportunity for the board to listen to the opinions of the
public
that relate to school and education matters on or off this evening's agenda.
The board is here to listen. Anyone wishing to speak, ask to proceed to the
microphone, state your name and the town or city where you reside.
All questions will be recorded by the superintendent and/or the chair or anyone
else up here who's helping, and will be answered by the end of public comment to
the extent possible. If answers are not available, someone will be assigned to
reply to you as soon as the answer is available.
You'll be given three minutes to speak.
No interaction between the public and board members, and additionally, no clapping,
booing, or other interruptive behavior will be allowed.
As a reminder, school board meetings are broadcast live, recorded, and posted on
the city's website. So please consider the impact of your
comments.
And you can go.
Thank you. Julia Edwards, Dawson Street.
I appreciate
everything that you all have gone through and your work and attention on this.
So turning to moving forward,
ironically, I wrote some comments on the back of my constitutional law
syllabus,
on the back of the page that deals with all of the nasty systemic
inequalities that have been enshrined in law for so long, that we are working to
now unwind. So I just want to make sure to call that out at every
possible opportunity and encourage anyone in this room or
watching to literally just Google Supreme
Court decisions on segregation, Supreme Court decisions on race,
Supreme Court decisions on gender, and start reading, because that's
how we got where we are here. So that's one thing
that I wanted to just say out loud because it's not being said enough.
And I apologize for my question before. I wasn't clear in what I meant.
My specific question about reaching families of students who are
not yet old enough to be in the schools was specific to the
five school family representation on the
steering committee that is now going to begin its work, and I think that that
committee is more crucial now than ever to get right
and to be as inclusive and dedicated to
reaching out to everybody that you possibly can.
And so I would like to ask for consideration that
perhaps a few additional, five additional seats be added to
include a family from each school that is not yet in the district.
All due respect to the board members, but you are board members, so that's not a
perspective that I think is...
There's a power dynamic there that I think correcting for by
bringing community members in would be helpful
to address. I also
want to point out that the city knows when people add children to
their families. We register them.
And so you know who has babies. You, the government, you
know who to reach and where they are and where they live and how old their
children are. So,
I know there's literally a spreadsheet on the state government website that
lists every single daycare and preschool in the entire state, and
you could reach out to all of them and be really creative
about how you reach people.
Flyers are not it, putting it in the city newsletter, no.
You need to reach people where they really are.
So, I think one thing that was a
disadvantage, or a dysfunction of the
previous leadership of the boundaries and configurations
work from my perspective as just a community member who wasn't in this district
yet.
There was not a lot of creative thinking around accessing
and bringing access to people who are not in the room.
So anytime you're building a-A committee that is
going to make big time, huge decisions behind closed doors,
I might add-
That's three minutes
... you really need to think about who's not in that room, and do your
damnedest to make sure that you've really exhausted all possibilities.
Just be creative. Thank you.
Thank you, Julia.
Hi.
Goodness, I'm sorry. Sarah Gay, parent, teacher, president of the
South Portland Teachers Association.
I am just passing along a request from one of my members that was sent to me about
two minutes ago, that the meet and greet sessions next
week be either live streamed or somehow accessible
digitally, given the number of our, particularly
members of our employee units who have children and other obligations outside of
their school day. That's all. Thank you.
Thank you, Sarah.
Aiden Renahan, a parent from Brown School.
I just want to really quickly say, I want to echo the comments
that I think this next phase of the reconfiguration implementation should be
looked at as an incredible opportunity to bring the community along.
I want to emphasize what Member Richardson said.
I think there is way more openness in this community than we are acknowledging.
You've got to speak into the mic.
Sorry. I think
there is way more openness to reconfiguration and this equity
discussion than we are giving credence to.
I do think there is much more nuance in people's views than being
for or against reconfiguration. I will speak for myself.
I think my central concern is that you cannot
manage what you do not measure. And the lack of quantification,
the lack of clear goals, the lack of illustration of the
resource and equity gaps and how this will solve it,
is what has me concerned. But I believe that can be
shown. I think the community cares about these gaps.
I think the community believes that these are all our children, and I think the
community would be incredibly alarmed to see these issues brought forth,
and incredibly motivated by a clear and quantifiable picture of how
reconfiguration can solve those gaps.
I also think it is incredibly powerful to the
community that do not have children in the district to see the financial
implications of a reconfiguration versus status quo scenario in
putting this district on financial footing.
So I really hope that we take the opportunity, despite the timeline to
November, to measure, to
bring this story forward, to put in clear and quantifiable goals
around the fiscal and programmatic impacts, and aspirational
education goals of what reconfiguration can achieve, and I think you
will be shocked at how many community members you can get on board.
Thank you very much.
Thank you very much, Aiden.
Hi, I'm Alex, South Portland parent.
I'm just going to read my questions again since they didn't get answered.
So,
the first question is, will you revisit the 2024 proposal,
the impact study, the consultant engagement, and the family input process and
review of comparable models, so that as we return to
reconfiguration, we return with evidence, community trust, and a real
plan?
So basically, will we revisit that, the kind of steps that were recommended
following the boundaries configuration study to then follow that plan through?
And
I referenced in my earlier public comment just that there were a few other
models such as magnet programs,
and choice schooling, all of that.
The second is, other than this reconfiguration steering committee,
how can parents engage meaningfully in larger conversations for
our schools? And this means things such as investments in arts program,
computer science, et cetera, other than public comment
or reaching out to school board members specifically. Thank you.
Thank you, Alex.
Hi there. Sarah Collins,
parent in the district.
So again, I wanted to ask, when people talk about
looking at is this budget neutral or how much is this going to cost, I realize
there are a lot of unknowns, a lot of this is conjecture.
I've heard that next year when it comes to reconfiguration, the next year
would've been budget neutral, or the first year would be budget neutral, but I
would love to see if there are projections for the cost saving in the longer term.
Again, I realize that's conjecture, but I feel like that's not being talked about
in this.
And again, just echoing, I think people get really caught up in the fear of
what this could involve and in the grief that we are at a loss,
the things that we are potentially missing out on.
But I think moving forward, we really need to focus on what are the positives, what
are the possibilities, what are the things that could be achieved with this moving
forward. So I agree with what people have said that we need to focus on that
messaging
moving forward, because I think there is a lot of nuance and a lot of opportunities
available with that.
And I also just want to make sure that we continue as a community to
find common ground, to see those places where we agree, because there's a lot of
division and a lot of challenges to this, but I think the way
that we speak to each other within this community is really important.
I think the way that we speak to the people that are serving us, whether we agree
with them or not, I think we need to be mindful of that.
Because there's a lot of emotion in this, but I think in the end, we have to come
together as a community to be able to do this.
And so in this next year, we have to keep that in mind.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, Sarah.
If there's no further
interest in public comment, public comment is closed.
We are up to school board communications.
Can we answer Alex's question?
Oh, I'm sorry.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I got three.
So her first question
was, well, what I
have, so Alex, you can correct me.What other
models will be used to look at during
this? And the second question, I think, was how can parents
engage more meaningfully? So I'm going to ask Dr.
Prince to talk about what roles of
parents may have moving forward.
I would like to comment on that, actually.
Oh, go ahead.
Yeah.
Please.
I'd like to comment on that. I
think, one, I'd love to see some larger engagement
from parents. It's absolutely needed.
One of the things would be we're launching the
South Portland School Foundation.
I don't know if that's the right name, but we're launching that.
That's an effort that's really going to need help.
That's a place where we really might be able to draw in some funds.
And it's going to need a lot of work.
Probably many of you have been involved in
fundraising and grant writing. It's not just
like, let's do it today, and it's all over.
It's an ongoing process that needs lots of work.
Another one is with parent-teacher organizations.
Like I mentioned earlier, that I'm in a conversation with somebody about some
creative ways to do some outreach that hasn't been done.
I think those are two
options. Another is that most school board meetings,
like of the committees, like policy or whatever, those are public meetings.
We did have a person who, he isn't here tonight, but he's been to a lot of these
meetings, who came to one of our finance committee meetings, for example, recently.
And it was interesting having him there.
We hardly ever have anyone come to those meetings.
Many of them are online, so they're pretty easy to attend.
That
is not intended to be exhaustive or a closed-end list, but those are some
options.
Can I add something?
Please.
Yeah, I think what parents can do, and this is a little bit of a
curveball answer, is advocate for responsible
development in South Portland. This is foundationally a money problem.
Right? And a 6% increase in the tax rate, if we
build more housing, that's going to be more money for schools. Right?
So,
yeah. I think thinking more about the root cause of the
issues that are so challenging right now and speaking to some of those
with your city council or just to your neighbors, I think, would be really helpful.
Thank you. Anybody have anything else?
And the other question,
I think, was what other models might be used to
be looked at other than reconfiguration.
Do I have that correct?
It's just revisiting- I think- ... the proposal from- Yeah.
Those were all the proposals, the
four or five proposals-
So, like recommendations
... from the boundaries and configurations recommendations.
Go back to that report and look at those things-
Yeah
... I think is what it meant.
Yeah.
Kind of.
And I think that that's going to be up to the
committee. So I would communicate with committee members
about that. And
Dr. Prince, is there a timeframe when the
committee members are going to be announced, or if you can speak to that?
Sure. So we've identified the first folks that we want to check in with.
I think when you indicate an interest, you also
need the opportunity then to see the dates and times of the meetings.
So we'll be working through that process of looking for a match
for folks that represent those constituents that I
talked about. So that will begin tomorrow,
and again, on the 8th when we meet, or
excuse me, the 11th when we meet again, we can provide an update and the names
and contact information of those individuals.
I think we'll have everyone confirmed by then.
Perfect. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
And we are up to if school board has any
communication. Member Feller.
So a, I guess, informal update from the Buildings and Grounds Committee, which-
Oh, well, we're not going to do that.
Well, okay. So it's just my communication. Fine.
So I've been talking to Revision
Energy about solar panels, and yeah, really good news
there is that just from a quick analysis of some of our
roofs, and especially the roofs that don't require imminent replacement, because
you don't want to put solar panels on a roof and then replace the roof a couple of
years later,
could save us between $300,000 and $500,000 annually.
And with financing, it wouldn't be a cost to the school.
So yeah, that will be an initiative, hopefully, of the Building and Grounds
Committee this summer and studied over a year's time.
But yeah, just something exciting to watch out for.
That's awesome. Thank you.
Anybody have anything else? Member Risch.
I'm going to make the call again. We owe it to future school boards to have a
policy on how we find a superintendent.
Maybe it's not the right place to have in the policy, but I would suggest it.
Thank you.
Anyone else? Seeing none,
this meeting is hereby adjourned. Thank you.
I just need signatures from-
Abigail keeps pointing at something.
Yeah, it's this.
We need to-
It's this